<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Oliver Z.</title>
    <link>https://oliz.io/blog</link>
    <description></description>
    <generator>Good Generator.py -- ggpy -- https://oliz.io/ggpy</generator>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 23 Oct 2021 19:10:31 -0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://oliz.io/blog/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>TIL: User Story Mapping</title>
      <link>https://oliz.io/blog/2018/user-story-mapping.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Oct 2018 20:18:58 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://oliz.io/blog/2018/user-story-mapping.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://manifesto.co.uk/user-story-mapping/"&gt;https://manifesto.co.uk/user-story-mapping/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the map dimensions being feature, process (user journey) and priority. Milestones are cut by priority, not by feature/process.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Smoother transitions between xmonad screens</title>
      <link>https://oliz.io/blog/2018/xcompmgr_init.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Feb 2018 02:44:21 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://oliz.io/blog/2018/xcompmgr_init.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;E.g. for presentations, &lt;code&gt;xcompmgr_init.sh&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="highlight"&gt;&lt;code&gt;#!/bin/bash

xcompmgr -f -C -n -D 3&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Three Months With a Fitness Tracker</title>
      <link>https://oliz.io/blog/2018/three-months-with-a-fitness-tracker.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Jun 2018 18:00:23 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://oliz.io/blog/2018/three-months-with-a-fitness-tracker.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In March I bought an entry-level fitness tracker ("Garmin Vivofit 3") for 50 €.
Being interested only in my daily step count and the distance/steps covered on various routine routes, I did not use any of the advanced features like sleep tracking or anything else that required interaction with the Garmin cloud.
Initializing the tracker required the creation of an account with my birthday (Jan 1st + accurate year 😉), height and mass.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Originally this blog post should have been called "One Month With a Fitness Tracker".
In fact I was barely using the tracker after the first month. So here are the results:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The tracker's measurement of distance was surprisingly accurate (to 10 meters, over the course of multiple 5 kilometer tracks), the step count/length was consistent between samples&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;As an office worker, going to the water dispenser or toilet is &lt;em&gt;not enough&lt;/em&gt; to get rid of the sedentary warning bar (for me around 400 steps seem to be required to get rid of the full bar)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Even on good (as in active) working days, I do not manage to cover 10000 steps (then the step count is within the 8000-9000 range)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Going to lunch outside the office adds at most 2000 steps&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Doing 10000 steps a day is equivalent to a 1.5 hour walk a day for me&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Due to the consistency of the measurements and me now knowing my metrics, I am mostly using the tracker as a watch now.
In fact, I only need to know how much time I spent covering a distance to deduct the steps and kilometers done.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Truth is in the Log</title>
      <link>https://oliz.io/blog/2018/the_truth_is_the_log.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Feb 2018 02:38:59 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://oliz.io/blog/2018/the_truth_is_the_log.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"The truth is the log. The database is a cache of a subset of the log."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Source: Pat Helland, Immutability Changes Everything, 2015&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>C. Headlee: 10 ways to have a better conversation</title>
      <link>https://oliz.io/blog/2018/10_ways_to_have_a_better_conversation.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Feb 2018 02:56:59 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://oliz.io/blog/2018/10_ways_to_have_a_better_conversation.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.ted.com/talks/celeste_headlee_10_ways_to_have_a_better_conversation"&gt;Celeste Headlee&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Listen!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Forget what you have heard!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don't multitask!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don't pontificate! (express one's opinions in a way considered annoyingly pompous and dogmatic)
   Assume that you have something to learn&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use open ended questions!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Go with the flow!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you don't know, say that you don't know!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don't equate your experience with their's!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Try not to repeat yourself!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Forget the details!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Listen!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Be brief!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Always be prepared to be amazed!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Why I Wrote yet Another Static Site Generator</title>
      <link>https://oliz.io/blog/2018/why-i-wrote-yet-another-static-site-gen.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Mar 2018 21:28:03 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://oliz.io/blog/2018/why-i-wrote-yet-another-static-site-gen.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Once a while somebody wants to write a blog post...&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Previously my website and blog hosted on GitHub were statically generated using &lt;a href="https://gohugo.io/"&gt;Hugo&lt;/a&gt;.
Even before Hugo I tried Jekyll, Pelican and was checking out &lt;a href="https://www.staticgen.com/"&gt;any site generator&lt;/a&gt;, that had at least some two-digit star count. Jekyll seemed too bloated and heavy-weight for my use case and the last time I looked into Pelican it had a license that I could not fully assess.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hugo certainly is a nice tool, but keeping track of updates and dependencies is annoying.
Even if I use a popular Hugo theme, I need to track updates of both Hugo and the theme.
Updates usually involve messing around in the configuration file as well.
Configuration files are almost always not compatible between different themes.
The same applies to the folder structure and canonical links.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="my-requirements"&gt;My Requirements&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I did not find a single &lt;abbr title="Static Site Generator"&gt;SSG&lt;/abbr&gt; fulfilling my personal requirements:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;dl&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Leverage free GitHub infrastructure&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;GitHub Pages is a real asset for me. Anything static, anything just running in someone's browser, I want to deploy using GitHub. Authentication is set up for development work already. Everything is free as in "tea". The behavior is really transparent:&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;GitHub Pages maps my repos nicely to its &lt;a href="https://ooz.github.io"&gt;github.io&lt;/a&gt; subdomain. A &lt;abbr title="Static Site Generator"&gt;SSG&lt;/abbr&gt; should be able to leverage the repository/directory structure!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;README.md&lt;/code&gt; files are rendered nicely on GitHub and can be edited there as well. So the &lt;abbr title="Static Site Generator"&gt;SSG&lt;/abbr&gt; should support rendering &lt;code&gt;README.md&lt;/code&gt; files as &lt;code&gt;index.html&lt;/code&gt; files for the repository/directory the file is located in!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to view the markdown file "as is" on GitHub, links to own assets/posts are usually broken in most SSGs due to templated links. GitHub Pages has Jekyll support included, but it is not as transparent as running Jekyll and deploying the result on your own.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Responsive design and pleasant typography&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Despite the mass of themes and free resources, this is still not a baseline. My website/blog should be nice to read everywhere and fonts should not strain the eye!&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Markdown support&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Life is too short to manually write plenty of markup. It was surprisingly hard to find a suitable markdown conversion tool/library, because there are so many dialects/extensions that lack proper implementation. I now decided for &lt;a href="https://python-markdown.github.io/extensions/"&gt;Python Markdown and its extensions&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Suitable not just for blog posts, but also for other content pages&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Some static site generators and themes are limited to specific use cases, I do not want to be restricted here.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Twitter Card, Open Graph support&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;This is covered by most themes, but it is again theme-dependent and if you develop your own theme, you need to take care of this also.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Portability&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Unix tools, bash, git, Python and some common apt packages are available even for my terminal emulator on Android. The tool should work in this environment.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Further there are lots of things solved by multiple SSGs that are &lt;em&gt;no requirements for me&lt;/em&gt;. An excerpt:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;dl&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Full local preview and draft support&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;I rather deploy fast and update a post incrementally if needed.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fast, incremental generation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;With my blogging frequency this might become an issue when the sun turns red...&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Big theme selection&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;I just need one working theme. &lt;abbr title="Static Site Generator"&gt;SSG&lt;/abbr&gt; themes are seldomly ranked, so it is hard to choose one to commit to.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Template engine, theme development option&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;See above, I just want something working to focus on writing content.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Why don't you just contribute to some project or develop your own theme?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I attempted to develop my own Hugo theme in the past, but I estimated the effort understanding all concepts and writing the archetypes, snippets and templates greater than just developing my own &lt;abbr title="Static Site Generator"&gt;SSG&lt;/abbr&gt;.
For the same reason contribution to another &lt;abbr title="Static Site Generator"&gt;SSG&lt;/abbr&gt; project was out of question: Too much effort catching up, esp. since most general purpose generators emphasize different features, that I do not need (see above).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So instead of investing time into things that might not yield the desired result, I decided to go my own path.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="my-solution"&gt;My Solution&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This blog and website are now generated by &lt;a href="https://github.com/ooz/ggpy"&gt;&lt;code&gt;gg.py&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, a single Python3 file inspired by &lt;a href="https://github.com/cfenollosa/bashblog"&gt;bashblog&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As CSS baseline I picked &lt;a href="https://milligram.io/"&gt;Milligram&lt;/a&gt;. It provides nice defaults without the need to put classes on every HTML element. This is especially handy, since I do not want to post-process the HTML generated from the Markdown input. Further dependencies include Google Fonts, Font Awesome and &lt;a href="https://highlightjs.org/"&gt;highlight.js&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Twitter cards and Open Graph meta data are rendered. The Python configuration file enables future preprocessing steps.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The mapping of GitHub repositories to (sub-)pages works nicely. Previous my website and blog were in the single repository &lt;a href="https://github.com/ooz/ooz.github.io"&gt;&lt;code&gt;ooz.github.io&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Now the &lt;a href="https://github.com/ooz/blog"&gt;&lt;code&gt;blog&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; has its own repository which fits in with the GitHub Pages of some personal projects (e.g. &lt;code&gt;ggpy&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;handshake&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;lifetime-clock&lt;/code&gt;). The new repository/page tree now looks like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="highlight"&gt;&lt;code&gt;ooz.github.io      # GitHub user page
├── index.html
├── blog
│   ├── index.html # Autogenerated from all blog posts
│   ├── 2018
│   │   ├── why-i-wrote-yet-another-static-site-gen.html
│   │   └── why-i-wrote-yet-another-static-site-gen.md
...
├── ggpy           # A normal repository page
├── handshake
├── lifetime-clock&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h2 id="open-ends"&gt;Open Ends&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Obviously, the 12-hour-hack solution is not feature complete and has some rough edges.
Things I am still looking forward to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;XML sitemap and RSS feed support&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Smarter top-level blog post index generation with older posts hidden and a tag cloud&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I thought about supporting Disqus as well, but I will probably rather include a "web 1.0" notice about using Twitter, GitHub issues or email to comment/contact me. This also reduces the attack vector of some German/EU bogus laws.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="generate-it-up"&gt;Generate it up!&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All in all I am pleased with the result so far.
The CSS framework, Markdown library and font selection were the biggest pain points costing a lot of development time.
Writing &lt;code&gt;gg.py&lt;/code&gt; was still a nice exercise: I learned about Twitter cards, Open Graph meta data formats and (re-)discovered some nice bash quirks in the source of &lt;a href="https://github.com/cfenollosa/bashblog/blob/master/bb.sh"&gt;bashblog&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The 25 Most Popular Icebreaker Questions</title>
      <link>https://oliz.io/blog/2018/the-25-most-popular-icebreaker-questions.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Jan 2018 20:39:03 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://oliz.io/blog/2018/the-25-most-popular-icebreaker-questions.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What was your first job?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Have you ever met anyone famous?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What are you reading right now?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you could pick up a new skill in an instant what would it be?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Who's someone you really admire?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Seen any good movies lately you'd recommend?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Got any favorite quotes?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Been pleasantly surprised by anything lately?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What was your favorite band 10 years ago?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What's your earliest memory?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Been anywhere recently for the first time?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What's your favorite family tradition?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Who had the most influence on you growing up?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What was the first thing you bought with your own money?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What's something you want to do in the next year that you've never done before?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Seen anything lately that made you smile?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What's your favorite place you've ever visited?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Have you had your 15 minutes of fame yet?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What's the best advice you've ever heard?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How do you like your eggs?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do you have a favorite charity you wish more people knew about?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Got any phobias you'd like to break?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Have you returned anything you've purchased recently? Why?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do you collect anything?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What's your favorite breakfast cereal?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href="https://m.signalvnoise.com/the-25-most-popular-icebreaker-questions-based-on-four-years-of-data/"&gt;https://m.signalvnoise.com/the-25-most-popular-icebreaker-questions-based-on-four-years-of-data/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Firefox Address Bar Search</title>
      <link>https://oliz.io/blog/2018/firefox-address-bar-search.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 May 2018 20:26:03 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://oliz.io/blog/2018/firefox-address-bar-search.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In Firefox's addressbar, you can limit results by typing special characters before or after your term&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="highlight"&gt;&lt;code&gt;^ for matches in your browsing history.
* for matches in your bookmarks.
% for matches in your currently open tabs.
# for matches in page titles.
@ for matches in web addresses.&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Copied from: &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/asadotzler/status/991061409839562752"&gt;https://twitter.com/asadotzler/status/991061409839562752&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bullshit Definition</title>
      <link>https://oliz.io/blog/2018/bullshit_definition.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Feb 2018 03:59:23 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://oliz.io/blog/2018/bullshit_definition.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The philosopher Harry Frankfurt at Princeton University defined bullshit as talk that has no relationship to the truth.
Lying covers up the truth, while bullshit is empty, and bears no relationship to the truth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href="https://aeon.co/ideas/how-to-fight-work-bullshit-and-keep-your-job-and-your-dignity"&gt;https://aeon.co/ideas/how-to-fight-work-bullshit-and-keep-your-job-and-your-dignity&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>grep_rename.sh</title>
      <link>https://oliz.io/blog/2018/grep_rename.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Feb 2018 03:23:19 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://oliz.io/blog/2018/grep_rename.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;pre class="highlight"&gt;&lt;code&gt;grep -rl 'old' ./ | xargs sed -i 's/old/new/g'&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>List gradle test execution order</title>
      <link>https://oliz.io/blog/2018/gradle-test-execution-order.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Aug 2018 02:53:42 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://oliz.io/blog/2018/gradle-test-execution-order.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;pre class="highlight"&gt;&lt;code&gt;tasks.matching {it instanceof Test}.all {
    testLogging.events = ["failed", "passed", "skipped"]
}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Useful for finding tests that do not clean up properly!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Code and Deploy on Android Using Termux</title>
      <link>https://oliz.io/blog/2018/code-and-deploy-using-termux.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Aug 2018 19:02:43 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://oliz.io/blog/2018/code-and-deploy-using-termux.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Publishing online is a rather easy task nowadays: Open some webpage or app, write something, add a few pictures and click the publish button. Done!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This blog does not have a fancy web UI nor a mobile app for administration purposes. It is statically generated using &lt;a href="https://github.com/ooz/ggpy"&gt;gg.py&lt;/a&gt;, a Python program, and published on GitHub Pages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So for me writing a blog post is not just writing, but also running Python programs, using git and deploying the result somewhere.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If I find a way to write my blog posts on a smartphone, I could in theory write plenty of other software on it as well, right?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="enter-termux"&gt;Enter Termux&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://wiki.termux.com/wiki/Main_Page"&gt;Termux&lt;/a&gt; is an Android terminal emulator featuring bash, Unix commandline tools, ssh and an apt-like package manager (incl. vim, git, Python etc.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After &lt;a href="https://wiki.termux.com/wiki/Touch_Keyboard"&gt;configuring the keyboard&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://github.com/ooz/olli"&gt;downloading my dotfiles&lt;/a&gt;, writing a blog post in vim looks like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Screenshot of vim running inside Termux" src="termux-blog-post.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The wiki also contains useful instructions on &lt;a href="https://wiki.termux.com/wiki/Internal_and_external_storage"&gt;how to access local files on your phone from inside Termux&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="peace-of-mind"&gt;Peace of mind&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Developing on a proper PC, with a proper keyboard is way faster and comfortable, of course.
Knowing that I do not just have access to the Internet on a phone, but that I could also actively shape it, lets me travel more comfortably without worrying too much about bringing a laptop. :)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Obstsalat</title>
      <link>https://oliz.io/blog/2018/obstsalat.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Feb 2018 02:13:04 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://oliz.io/blog/2018/obstsalat.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Äpfel&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Birnen&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Orangen&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Grapefruit&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pomelo&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Chikoree&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Walnüsse&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Banane&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Plus:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2 Zitronen (Saft)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Zucker&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Prime Directive</title>
      <link>https://oliz.io/blog/2018/the_prime_directive.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Feb 2018 02:47:31 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://oliz.io/blog/2018/the_prime_directive.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"Regardless of what we discover, we understand and truly believe that everyone did the best job they could, given what they knew at the time, their skills and abilities, the resources available, and the situation at hand."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Source: Norm Kerth, Project Retrospectives: A Handbook for Team Review&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dell Trackpoint Fix</title>
      <link>https://oliz.io/blog/2018/dell_trackpoint_fix.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Feb 2018 04:00:53 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://oliz.io/blog/2018/dell_trackpoint_fix.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Alter Dell laptop trackpoint sensitivity under Linux:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="highlight"&gt;&lt;code&gt;xinput list
xinput list-props 13
xinput set-prop 13 269 1.0
xinput set-prop 13 269 0.8
xinput set-prop 13 269 0.5
xinput set-prop 13 269 0.1
xinput set-prop 13 268 0.5
xinput set-prop 13 268 0.9
xinput list-props 13
xinput set-prop 13 267 0.9
xinput set-prop 13 267 0.1
xinput set-prop 13 267 2.0
xinput set-prop 13 268 2.0
xinput set-prop 13 268 1.0
xinput set-prop 13 269 0.05
xinput set-prop 13 267 3.0
xinput set-prop 13 267 5.0
xinput set-prop 13 268 2.0
xinput set-prop 13 268 1.5
xinput set-prop 13 267 1.0
xinput set-prop 13 267 2.0
xinput set-prop 13 267 3.0
xinput set-prop 13 267 4.0
xinput set-prop 13 268 2.0
xinput list-props 13
xinput set-prop 13 267 2.5
xinput set-prop 13 268 1.0
xinput set-prop 13 269 12.5
xinput set-prop 13 267 5.0
xinput set-prop 13 267 7.0
xinput set-prop 13 268 2.0
xinput set-prop 13 267 10.0
xinput set-prop 13 268 3.0
xinput set-prop 13 268 5.0
xinput set-prop 13 267 15.0
xinput set-prop 13 267 12.0
xinput set-prop 13 267 11.0

# $ xinput list-props 13
# Device 'AlpsPS/2 ALPS DualPoint Stick':
#   Device Enabled (140):   1
#   Coordinate Transformation Matrix (142): 1.000000, 0.000000, 0.000000, 0.000000, 1.000000, 0.000000, 0.000000, 0.000000, 1.000000
#   Device Accel Profile (266): 0
#   Device Accel Constant Deceleration (267):   11.000000
#   Device Accel Adaptive Deceleration (268):   5.000000
#   Device Accel Velocity Scaling (269):    12.500000
#   Device Product ID (261):    2, 8
#   Device Node (262):  "/dev/input/event6"
#   Evdev Axis Inversion (305): 0, 0
#   Evdev Axes Swap (307):  0
#   Axis Labels (308):  "Rel X" (150), "Rel Y" (151)
#   Button Labels (309):    "Button Left" (143), "Button Middle" (144), "Button Right" (145), "Button Wheel Up" (146), "Button Wheel Down" (147), "Button Horiz Wheel Left" (148), "Button Horiz Wheel Right" (149)
#   Evdev Scrolling Distance (310): 0, 0, 0
#   Evdev Middle Button Emulation (311):    1
#   Evdev Middle Button Timeout (312):  50
#   Evdev Third Button Emulation (313): 0
#   Evdev Third Button Emulation Timeout (314): 1000
#   Evdev Third Button Emulation Button (315):  3
#   Evdev Third Button Emulation Threshold (316):   20
#   Evdev Wheel Emulation (317):    1
#   Evdev Wheel Emulation Axes (318):   6, 7, 4, 5
#   Evdev Wheel Emulation Inertia (319):    10
#   Evdev Wheel Emulation Timeout (320):    200
#   Evdev Wheel Emulation Button (321): 2
#   Evdev Drag Lock Buttons (322):  0&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Upgrading to Ubuntu 18.04</title>
      <link>https://oliz.io/blog/2018/upgrading-to-ubuntu-1804.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Nov 2018 23:08:49 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://oliz.io/blog/2018/upgrading-to-ubuntu-1804.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;So far I upgraded three Ubuntu machines from 16.04 LTS to 18.04 LTS.
Just my work laptop is left. A little checklist for future upgrades:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="before-upgrading"&gt;Before upgrading&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cleanup unneeded packages to minimize the need to update&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="upgrade"&gt;Upgrade!&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do the actual upgrade to Ubuntu 18.04:
    &lt;pre class="highlight"&gt;&lt;code class="language-bash"&gt;sudo apt update
sudo do-release-upgrade&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Add PPA for &lt;a href="https://github.com/Gekkio/gnome-session-xmonad"&gt;Gnome + XMonad&lt;/a&gt; again:
    &lt;pre class="highlight"&gt;&lt;code class="language-bash"&gt;sudo add-apt-repository ppa:gekkio/xmonad
sudo apt-get update
sudo apt-get install gnome-session-xmonad&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Select &lt;code&gt;GNOME + XMonad&lt;/code&gt; session at login&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="polish"&gt;Polish&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Install Gnome tweak tool:
    &lt;pre class="highlight"&gt;&lt;code class="language-bash"&gt;sudo apt install gnome-tweak-tool&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use &lt;code&gt;gnome-tweaks&lt;/code&gt; to hide desktop icons (category by category, hiding all at once resets the wallpaper as well!)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Backup wineprefix under &lt;code&gt;~/.wine&lt;/code&gt;, let wine 3.0 initialize the default wineprefix again, e.g. by executing &lt;code&gt;winecfg&lt;/code&gt;. Then copy relevant programs back into the wineprefix&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Update: previously it was needed to adapt the Gnome configuration in regards to top/bottom panels.
If this features ever surfaces again:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Install &lt;code&gt;dconf-editor&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Go to entry &lt;code&gt;org &amp;gt; gnome &amp;gt; gnome-panel &amp;gt; layout&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For  key &lt;code&gt;toplevel-id-list&lt;/code&gt; remove &lt;code&gt;'bottom-panel'&lt;/code&gt; from list&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bad Code</title>
      <link>https://oliz.io/blog/2018/bad-code.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Aug 2018 17:04:02 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://oliz.io/blog/2018/bad-code.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Today, I discovered three distinct cases of poorly written code in our team's code base. Each time it bothered me so much, that before improving, I checked the author of those lines: me, a year ago.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Communication Misunderstandings (K. Lorenz)</title>
      <link>https://oliz.io/blog/2018/communication-misunderstandings.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Sep 2018 02:37:04 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://oliz.io/blog/2018/communication-misunderstandings.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Konrad Lorenz:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Thought is not said&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Said is not heard&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Heard is not understood&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Understood is not agreed&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Agreed is not done&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Done is not continued&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Continued is not valid for ever&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>My Interview Checklist</title>
      <link>https://oliz.io/blog/2018/my-interview-checklist/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Dec 2018 01:35:18 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://oliz.io/blog/2018/my-interview-checklist/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Heavily inspired by and copied from &lt;a href="https://jvns.ca/blog/2013/12/30/questions-im-asking-in-interviews/"&gt;Julia Evans' "Questions I'm asking in interviews"&lt;/a&gt;.
I intend to use this from both sides of the table: when I am the interviewee and when I need to gauge a candidate's interest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="research"&gt;Research&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Could be answered by up-front investigation:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How does the company make money?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Does the business model scale?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Any ethical concerns regarding the business model?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="questions"&gt;Questions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Questions to ask ordered by stage (when to ask in the interviewing process) and topic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How is the interview process structured?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id="organization-management-culture"&gt;Organization, management, culture&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How does the on-boarding process look like?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How does internal communication work? Tools? Hierarchies? No-gos?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How are (technical / architectural) decisions made?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Are the company revenue, profit and cost structure transparent for employees?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is your turnover rate (devs hired-to-lost-ratio last/this year?)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is it possible to move to other locations of the company?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How many hours does senior management work per week (CEO/CTO)?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do you think there is any company benefit that is over-the-top, unfair or a waste of money?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What do you think is the biggest challenge in the team/department/company right now? How do you address it?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id="career-community"&gt;Career, community&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How is performance evaluated?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Can you give me an example of someone who’s been in a technical role at your company for a long time, and how their responsibilities and role have changed?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do you contribute to open source projects (project names, which teams)?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do you encourage employees to speak at conferences/universities? How are they supported? Could you name the last talk your company supported (speaker/topic/event)?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is the education budget? Are travel costs to conferences covered? How is money/time needed for education balanced?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How do you address plateauing and mental health?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id="development-team"&gt;Development, team&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Adapted &lt;a href="https://www.joelonsoftware.com/2000/08/09/the-joel-test-12-steps-to-better-code/"&gt;Joel Test&lt;/a&gt;, less binary, more Julia questions. Let's call it "Joel &amp;amp; Julia Test" (or "JJ Test"):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Which version control system do you use?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do new candidates write code during their interview?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How do you track bugs, tasks?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Can you make a build in one step? Test environment in one step?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do you make daily builds?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How does your deployment process look like?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do you fix bugs before writing new code?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;May I see some of the code the team has written?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do programmers have quiet working conditions?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do you have testers, designers, tech writers?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How is your roadmap determined?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;May I use/test/see your software right now?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id="other"&gt;Other&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When and why did you join this company?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Flexi-time?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I need one day in home office on short notice. Who needs to approve this?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Number of vacation days? If unlimited: how many are taken on average? Is unpaid vacation/sabbatical possible?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Average number of work hours per week? What are the peaks?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;On call duty? How often? Work on weekends? Special benefits?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Am I required to travel for this position? How often?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do people "login" during vacation? How often?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How often do you offer above the requested salary? May I speak with someone who got such an offer?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="while-on-site"&gt;While on-site&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Observe office space layout/organization&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Observe developer desks: Multiple screens? Good panels? What is the dominant non-Mac computer brand?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Check bathroom. Any shortage of soap/paper towels towards the end of the year?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Could the outside smoking area affect the office climate?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Water dispenser, kitchen?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="questions-for-potential-team-mates"&gt;Questions for potential team mates&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Could be one prepared A4 printout per person)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;First name? Position/role/task in team? Time with the company?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What program windows do you have open on your PC right now?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Which one is correct and why: 1. Compress, then encrypt or 2. encrypt, then compress?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In computing, what is a &lt;em&gt;signature&lt;/em&gt;? What properties does it have? What is the use-case?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Open-ended coding task asking "how would you improve this piece of code?" Watch out for data structure usage (set/list test), whether they would mention tests, naming&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Makefile Hacks</title>
      <link>https://oliz.io/blog/2021/makefile-hacks.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Oct 2021 02:40:13 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://oliz.io/blog/2021/makefile-hacks.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://blog.melski.net/2010/11/30/makefile-hacks-print-the-value-of-any-variable/"&gt;Makefile variable debugging&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://victoria.dev/blog/how-to-create-a-self-documenting-makefile/"&gt;Self-documenting Makefile&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a href="https://github.com/ooz/ggpy/blob/master/Makefile"&gt;example&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>If computers are bicycles for our minds [†], then smartphones are clown shoes for our attention.</title>
      <link>https://oliz.io/blog/2021/bicycle-for-our-minds.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 Oct 2021 22:54:45 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://oliz.io/blog/2021/bicycle-for-our-minds.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;† Steve Jobs: &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=rTRzYjoZhIY"&gt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=rTRzYjoZhIY&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>BIOS Keys by Manufacturer</title>
      <link>https://oliz.io/blog/2021/bios-keys.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Sep 2021 21:12:13 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://oliz.io/blog/2021/bios-keys.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Manufacturer&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Key&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Acer&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Esc, F2, F9, F12&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Apple&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Option&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Asus&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Esc&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Clevo&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;F7&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Dell&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;F12&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Fujitsu&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Esc, F12&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;HP&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;F9&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Huawei&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;F12&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Intel&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;F10&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Lenovo&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;F12&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;MSI&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;F11&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Samsung&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Esc, F2, F12&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Sony&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Esc, F10, F11&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Toshiba&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;F12&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;others...&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Esc, F12&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href="https://tails.boum.org/install/linux/usb/index.en.html"&gt;https://tails.boum.org/install/linux/usb/index.en.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Five Phases of an Operation</title>
      <link>https://oliz.io/blog/2021/five-phases-of-an-operation.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Oct 2021 21:26:06 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://oliz.io/blog/2021/five-phases-of-an-operation.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Target Selection&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Planning (and Surveillance)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Deployment&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Execution&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Escape and Evasion&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href="https://grugq.github.io/blog/2013/12/21/in-search-of-opsec-magic-sauce/"&gt;https://grugq.github.io/blog/2013/12/21/in-search-of-opsec-magic-sauce/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pulse Width Modulation (PWM) and Mobile Screens</title>
      <link>https://oliz.io/blog/2021/pwm-screen-ranking.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Aug 2021 20:43:46 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://oliz.io/blog/2021/pwm-screen-ranking.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.notebookcheck.com/PWM-Ranking-Welche-Notebooks-Smartphones-und-Tablets-nutzen-PWM.163974.0.html"&gt;https://www.notebookcheck.com/PWM-Ranking-Welche-Notebooks-Smartphones-und-Tablets-nutzen-PWM.163974.0.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;0&lt;/code&gt; is best, meaning "no PWM". Otherwise higher frequency is better. Sensitive people may have issues with screens in the 250-500 Hz range or lower frequencies.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Time Tracking</title>
      <link>https://oliz.io/blog/2021/home-office-time-tracking/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 29 May 2021 21:22:41 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://oliz.io/blog/2021/home-office-time-tracking/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Having worked in home office mode for a few months before the Corona pandemic hit, I felt like spending too much time working without knowing, how long I actually work each day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being on flexitime and 40h/week, I often compensated for small breaks or distractions.
So I wanted a proper time tracking solution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="requirements"&gt;Requirements&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Simple start/stop user interface&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Track work time per day and per week&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Data is saved in a simple format&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tool may be used for project-based time tracking&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ideally, I wanted a separate single-use device (smartphone/web browser ruled out) with a start/stop button and a small display.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="consumerist-detour"&gt;Consumerist Detour&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead of writing the program first, &lt;a href="https://shop.m5stack.com/products/stick-c"&gt;I went shopping for a device which suited my interface needs&lt;/a&gt;. In the midst of the pandemic:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Straight from Shenzhen" src="m5stick-c_delivery.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Some steps edited out for brevity)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After toying around with the device for an evening, digging through part-English, part-Chinese documentation, eventually setting up UiFlow, connecting the device and getting a simple visually programmed (but wrong) program to run... I put the project to rest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-solution"&gt;The Solution&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The time tracking problem didn't magically disappear, so a few weeks ago I solved it with a &lt;a href="https://github.com/ooz/olli/blob/master/.scripts/punchcard.py"&gt;simple Python script&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Executing the script starts the timer:
&lt;pre class="highlight"&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ punchcard.py
Clocking in at  2021-05-29 23:08:56.477436&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Terminating the script prints time worked in the current session, today and for the week:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="highlight"&gt;&lt;code&gt;^C
Clocking out at 2021-05-29 23:09:29.253941 (after 32s)
Today: 32s
This week: 32h 16m&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every five minutes it prints the time tracked so far. All data is saved in &lt;code&gt;.punchcard.csv&lt;/code&gt; in current directory. The format is the date followed by seconds tracked that day:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="highlight"&gt;&lt;code&gt;DATE,SECONDS
2021-05-29,32&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The printed output and simple format also makes it easy to correct wrongly tracked time (e.g. when forgetting to start/terminate the script). Time may be tracked for different projects, even in parallel by starting the script in different (project-specific) directories, in separate terminals or as background processes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="lesson-learned"&gt;Lesson Learned&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The script works and the "separate, single-use device" became a separate virtual desktop with just the time tracking terminal(s).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recently, I fetched the M5StickC again and tried to port the program to &lt;a href="https://docs.micropython.org/en/latest/esp32/quickref.html"&gt;MicroPython&lt;/a&gt;, which uses Python 2 syntax and has less batteries included (e.g. no high-level datetime package). I ended up with a &lt;a href="punchcard_stopwatch.py"&gt;stripped-down version of the punchcard script, a simple stopwatch&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Glorified stopwatch code" src="mc_stopwatch_code.png" /&gt;
&lt;img alt="Glorified stopwatch on M5StickC" src="mc_stopwatch.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;UiFlow is nice for exploring the device API and supplied widgets, since you can compose some visual program using all desired features (e.g. sensors, UI components) and then inspect the generated Python code (however, you can't freely switch between the views: the program/source gets reset!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, I didn't put more effort in the ESP32 microcontroller solution, because the script already covers my needs. Writing the script and doing more research first would have saved me ~15 €, but I still learned something tinkering around with the device.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Master Thesis M. Beschnidt: Sensomotorik und Handlungskompetenz</title>
      <link>https://oliz.io/blog/2021/sensomotorik-und-handlungskompetenz/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 21 Aug 2021 22:58:18 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://oliz.io/blog/2021/sensomotorik-und-handlungskompetenz/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The thesis is roughly structured in three parts.
First, the author researches theory, definitions, commons grounds in sports science and neuroscience.
He then formulates three hypotheses, which are falsified after further literature research and deductions.
Last, the findings are further confirmed by four examples from his experience as a &lt;a href="https://sendo-karate.com/professionelle-betreuung"&gt;karate trainer&lt;/a&gt; and as a occupational safety instructor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Key findings:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;"Wiederholen ohne Wiederholung" (from &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nikolai_Bernstein"&gt;N. Bernstein&lt;/a&gt;, 1996, rough English translation: "repeat without repetition") holds true: quality of every movement matters. Coordination and learning effect improve when conditions are changed and the trainee is challenged (rooted in different levels of concious effort and mechanic movement automation).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Energy reserves for cognitive tasks are limited (untrained 360-460 kcal, in liver), glycolysis&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Muscles have glycogen storage which cannot be accessed by the nervous system. Muscles use glycolysis, then lipolysis (burning fats) and ketogenesis. The latter are energy-inefficient and put stress on the immune system.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Thus mental and physical exhaustion are interdependent.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A holistic approach to training is advised, proper (physical) training boosts not just specific but also general competence. Important aspects of such training are highlighted.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Identifying bad technological assistance systems causing stress and sensory overload. Instead, technology should automate and assist, not distract.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Emotional level matters for building competence, too.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="my-learnings"&gt;My Learnings&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was surprised to learn that the effectiveness of &lt;em&gt;Shisa Kanko&lt;/em&gt; ("finger pointing and calling", &lt;a href="https://youtu.be/D8A_Hu_WqeQ?t=317"&gt;example&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://youtu.be/gjCzavpZoZI?t=726"&gt;another one&lt;/a&gt;) is well-supported by science and aligned with the thesis' findings.
Before, it looked like a misguided Japanese efficiency ritual or make-work to me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From my observation, the holistic learning/teaching approach is also applicable to "thought work" like computer science and software engineering:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It's not enough to learn the theory, it needs to be applied and used regularly.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Raw repetition is not valuable. Quality, variety and challenge matter to grow in the profession.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ties in with understanding and interdependence of language, intelligence, physical affordances and perception of "the real world". How related research on language, intelligence, child development, AI, sports and design is converging (which should probably be a blog post of its own).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In general, separation of "body and mind" &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ren%C3%A9_Descartes#Mind%E2%80%93Body_Dualism"&gt;rooted in western philosophy&lt;/a&gt; can be seen as an ill-path.
Or like the Romans used to say:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mens_sana_in_corpore_sano"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mens sana in corpore sano&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Towards Online Autonomy</title>
      <link>https://oliz.io/blog/2021/towards-online-autonomy/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 06 Jun 2021 21:49:18 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://oliz.io/blog/2021/towards-online-autonomy/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Smartphones have become the "personal computer":
a computer in your hand, solving most of your consumer computer use-cases (e.g. communication, (re-)search, navigation, shopping, photo, video, music, social and other media).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ever since, I'm annoyed, that we don't (can't) really &lt;em&gt;own&lt;/em&gt; smartphones like we can own other computing equipment.
Smartphones have hard- and software obsolescence built-in.
They are tailored towards consumption and guided interactions, most of the time they are inferior tools for creation.
Users may perceive value from interacting with a smartphone, but the majority of interactions generate more revenue/profit for other entities through &lt;a href="https://oliz.io/blog/2020/dev-talk-binge-random-wisdom/#attention-economy"&gt;attention economy&lt;/a&gt;
(making platforms more attractive for other users, network effects, data classification, entry and generation etc.)
If you don't use your smartphone to make money (media creator, influencer?), you are paying -sometimes premium- for being used and distracted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="tech-is-getting-consolidated"&gt;Tech is Getting Consolidated...&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This entire development didn't start and won't end with smartphones.
&lt;a href="https://stallman.org/"&gt;RMS&lt;/a&gt; has been anticipating and warning about it for decades already (see his &lt;a href="https://stallman.org/glossary.html#used"&gt;definition of "Useds"&lt;/a&gt;). It's common knowledge by now, some examples:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hardware backdoors (&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Intel_Management_Engine"&gt;Intel ME&lt;/a&gt;, undocumented x86 instructions) in mainline processors&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://staltz.com/the-web-began-dying-in-2014-heres-how.html"&gt;The internet becoming more centralized&lt;/a&gt; with &lt;a href="https://www.visualcapitalist.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/08/top-100-websites-ranking.html"&gt;a dozen of mega corporations owning the majority of the traffic&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In the near future, &lt;a href="https://sneak.berlin/20201112/your-computer-isnt-yours/"&gt;we'll get smartphone-level surveillance and "ownership" for our other computers, too&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://oliz.io/blog/2021/pegasus-android-check/"&gt;Pegasus anyone?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Expiring computers may be fine for most companies leasing or cycling every 2-3 years and some users, who rotate in a similar fashion to "stay on the edge".
In my opinion, sustainable, exhaustive tech usage should be preferred, which is also dependent on &lt;em&gt;user-serviceable&lt;/em&gt;, secure hard- and software.
State and malicious actors may like loopholes, but &lt;a href="https://www.wired.com/story/power-grid-cyberattack-facebook-phone-numbers-security-news/"&gt;insecure infrastructure ultimately harms everyone&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The general population (not just the nerds) is spending more screentime consuming social media, streaming content and games. Thus we are increasingly exposed to and determined by the above developments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="and-boring"&gt;...and Boring&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Starting in 2019, I noticed how I barely got any value out of Twitter anymore. Of course, there was the occasional interesting tech news, story or funny pastime, but interacting with it felt like a chore. So I stopped using it, although I haven't migrated my content away from it, yet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another wake-up call has been &lt;a href="https://blog.google/products/photos/storage-changes/"&gt;Google Photos' changed storage policy&lt;/a&gt;: Unlimited photo storage and sync has been so convenient. Google profited greatly from all the training data! Now that the noise is increasing and the value is diminishing, economics are back to remind us all: "Useds" of a free service don't own anything.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, this sped up my migration away from my previously central &lt;code&gt;gmail.com&lt;/code&gt; address towards my own &lt;code&gt;oliz.io&lt;/code&gt; domain in 2020. I evaluated my exposure to and reliance on "big tech", too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="progress-so-far-to-be-updated-over-time"&gt;Progress so Far (to Be Updated Over Time)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Autonomy gained:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="task-list"&gt;
&lt;li class="task-list-item"&gt;&lt;input type="checkbox" disabled checked/&gt; Acquire &lt;code&gt;oliz.io&lt;/code&gt; domain in 2020&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li class="task-list-item"&gt;&lt;input type="checkbox" disabled checked/&gt; Use &lt;a href="https://mailbox.org"&gt;https://mailbox.org&lt;/a&gt; with own domain for email&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li class="task-list-item"&gt;&lt;input type="checkbox" disabled checked/&gt; Build static website on &lt;code&gt;oliz.io&lt;/code&gt; domain, using &lt;a href="https://oliz.io/ggpy/"&gt;&lt;code&gt;gg.py&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li class="task-list-item"&gt;&lt;input type="checkbox" disabled/&gt; Migrate contacts to KeePass&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li class="task-list-item"&gt;&lt;input type="checkbox" disabled/&gt; Find good, local solution for keeping track of birthdays (master data in KeePass)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stopped/minimized using:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="task-list"&gt;
&lt;li class="task-list-item"&gt;&lt;input type="checkbox" disabled checked/&gt; &lt;strong&gt;XING&lt;/strong&gt;: Used its "one year pause" mode which recently expired, it spammed me again and I deleted it permanently.
                Preferring LinkedIn (and considering moving my data out there, too)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;LinkedIn&lt;/strong&gt;: Doing minimal effort there, keeping resume up-to-date and accepting connections I either know or who seem to be real humans reading profiles.
                Too much and not valuable recruiter spam made me lock down notification settings and network exposure, &lt;a href="https://blog.calebjay.com/posts/how-to-use-linkedin-as-a-coding-bootcamp-grad/"&gt;but then again I'm probably not using it right&lt;/a&gt;. The CV tooling is neat, still I may just abandon it at some point and put the resume on here&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li class="task-list-item"&gt;&lt;input type="checkbox" disabled checked/&gt; &lt;strong&gt;GitHub Gists&lt;/strong&gt;: Integrated into this blog using &lt;a href="https://oliz.io/ggpy/"&gt;ggpy's&lt;/a&gt; new micro-blogging functionality.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li class="task-list-item"&gt;&lt;input type="checkbox" disabled/&gt; &lt;strong&gt;Gmail&lt;/strong&gt;: Contacts aren't migrated yet. Haven't actively reached out to anyone regarding the email change, yet&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Amazon&lt;/strong&gt;: In general, I prefer to buy in local or specialized (online) shops. Amazon still has the superior customer service and return/refund policy, so I may go with it for uncertain/risky purchases.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kept using:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;GitHub&lt;/strong&gt; (&lt;a href="https://sneak.berlin/20200307/the-case-against-microsoft-and-github/"&gt;Microsoft is a serious offender&lt;/a&gt;): I still use it due to convenience, but everything is static, in Git and under my domain. So, migration to any other service is pretty easy when ultimately needed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Google / Android&lt;/strong&gt;: Despite Google having converged towards the average user, it's still unparalleled. Sometimes I use duckduckgo for easy stuff. Smartphone usage is work-related (2FA/Authy, communication)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dropbox&lt;/strong&gt;: Proprietary daemon running in the background at all times, what could possibly go wrong?! Still using due to convenience, &lt;a href="https://www.grepular.com/Protecting_Your_GNU_Linux_System_from_Dropbox"&gt;here is a guide to isolate the process&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://vscodium.com/"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;VSCodium&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;: Microsoft-free VSCode, plus &lt;a href="https://github.com/ooz/olli/blob/master/.vimrc"&gt;&lt;code&gt;vim&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; of course&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Educate others:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Setup your own domain and &lt;a href="https://sneak.berlin/20201029/stop-emailing-like-a-rube/"&gt;use it for email&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don't buy into/use "walled garden ecosystems", look for alternatives, e.g. on &lt;del&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.privacytools.io"&gt;https://www.privacytools.io&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/del&gt;, &lt;a href="https://privacyguides.org"&gt;https://privacyguides.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Twitter&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="task-list"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Not using it anymore&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li class="task-list-item"&gt;&lt;input type="checkbox" disabled/&gt; WIP: Migrating my content to this blog&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li class="task-list-item"&gt;&lt;input type="checkbox" disabled/&gt; I still need a solution to follow some people I know or like&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li class="task-list-item"&gt;&lt;input type="checkbox" disabled/&gt; Add RSS feed generation to ggpy to make it easier for others to subscribe to my content&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="further-inspiration-and-links"&gt;Further Inspiration and Links&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Certainly, I'm not the first to be alienated. So here are a bunch of other nice, informative websites/blogs by people following the same idea of an independent internet:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://victoria.dev/blog/make-your-own-independent-website/"&gt;https://victoria.dev/blog/make-your-own-independent-website/&lt;/a&gt; (note to self: have a look at webmention)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://sneak.berlin/20200220/discord-is-not-an-acceptable-choice-for-free-software-projects/"&gt;Free messaging alternatives&lt;/a&gt; (haha, this entire post reeks of &lt;a href="https://sneak.berlin"&gt;sneak.berlin&lt;/a&gt;, great content!)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://riseup.net/"&gt;https://riseup.net/&lt;/a&gt; (various independent communication and collaboration services)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://webbkoll.dataskydd.net/en"&gt;Website privacy checker&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://madaidans-insecurities.github.io/"&gt;General security flaws with modern tech&lt;/a&gt; (nice, minimal website, too!)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://gitlab.com/linuxcafefederation/awesome-android/-/blob/main/README.md"&gt;Curated list of libre Android apps&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Checking an Android Phone for NSO Group&amp;#x27;s Pegasus Malware</title>
      <link>https://oliz.io/blog/2021/pegasus-android-check/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Jul 2021 22:40:11 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://oliz.io/blog/2021/pegasus-android-check/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;After &lt;a href="https://www.amnesty.org/en/latest/research/2021/07/forensic-methodology-report-how-to-catch-nso-groups-pegasus/"&gt;Amnesty International’s Methodology Report&lt;/a&gt; from last Sunday, I early-adopted the &lt;a href="https://github.com/mvt-project/mvt"&gt;Mobile Verification Toolkit&lt;/a&gt; on Monday evening.
At that time, parts of the documentation and cross-referencing were pretty basic, so I'm documenting my process and concentrating links to all resources here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Less tech-savvy users may want to wait for the &lt;a href="https://github.com/mvt-project/mvt/issues/38"&gt;announced GUI&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Preconditions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Have &lt;code&gt;adb&lt;/code&gt; installed or use the &lt;a href="https://github.com/mvt-project/mvt/pull/16"&gt;Docker image&lt;/a&gt; (this saves some MVT installation steps, too)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://developer.android.com/studio/debug/dev-options#enable"&gt;Enable developer mode on the Android device, enable USB debugging in developer options&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Further read:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://info.lookout.com/rs/051-ESQ-475/images/lookout-pegasus-technical-analysis.pdf"&gt;Lookout's Analysis of Pegasus Spyware (2016 version)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="installing-mvt-in-a-pipenv"&gt;Installing MVT in a pipenv&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I installed the project's dependencies in a &lt;a href="https://pipenv.pypa.io/en/latest/"&gt;&lt;code&gt;pipenv&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; to not pollute the system's python packages and &lt;code&gt;$PATH&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="highlight"&gt;&lt;code class="language-bash"&gt;# Clone repository
git clone https://github.com/mvt-project/mvt.git
cd mvt/

# Install dependencies in pipenv
pipenv --python 3
pipenv run pip3 install .&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h2 id="check-apks-for-malware-signatures"&gt;&lt;a href="https://mvt-docs.readthedocs.io/en/latest/android/download_apks.html"&gt;Check APKs for malware signatures&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since you can't use the tool to download the APKs and check for malware signatures later,
it's best to do this right away.
Otherwise you'd need to download the packages twice:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="highlight"&gt;&lt;code class="language-bash"&gt;mkdir android-apks
pipenv run mvt-android download-apks -o android-apks/ --virustotal&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes the Android device is busy and MVT recommends to reset the &lt;code&gt;adb&lt;/code&gt; server. This works just fine:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="highlight"&gt;&lt;code class="language-bash"&gt;adb kill-server&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the phone, when downloading the APKs, you will be asked (multiple times, even if you check the 'allow future access' box) to allow &lt;code&gt;adb&lt;/code&gt; access, this dialog needs to be accepted within 5 seconds, otherwise MVT times out. It's best to be attentive and watch the phone screen. ;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="check-sms-backup-for-malicious-links"&gt;Check SMS backup for malicious links&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This process is &lt;a href="https://mvt-docs.readthedocs.io/en/latest/android/backup.html"&gt;well-documented&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A malware definition file in &lt;a href="https://github.com/AmnestyTech/investigations/tree/master/2021-07-18_nso"&gt;STIX v2 format (pegasus.stix2)&lt;/a&gt; is needed. MVT is not compatible with STIX v1.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Also, &lt;a href="https://github.com/nelenkov/android-backup-extractor/releases"&gt;Android Backup Extractor&lt;/a&gt; is needed. Download &lt;code&gt;abe.jar&lt;/code&gt; from the releases page.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;pre class="highlight"&gt;&lt;code class="language-bash"&gt;# Backup SMS from Android device
adb backup com.android.providers.telephony

# Extract SMS backup
java -jar abe.jar unpack backup.ab backup.tar
tar xvf backup.tar

# Check backup against STIX v2 file
pipenv run mvt-android check-backup . --iocs pegasus.stix2&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>J. Langr on Twitter: Top IntelliJ IDEA refactoring keys</title>
      <link>https://oliz.io/blog/2019/top-intellij-idea-refactoring-shortcuts.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 Dec 2019 14:15:49 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://oliz.io/blog/2019/top-intellij-idea-refactoring-shortcuts.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/jlangr/status/1204482861845250048"&gt;Jeff Langr&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;top IntelliJ IDEA refactoring keys:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;extract Method: Cmd-Alt-M&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;extract Variable: Cmd-Alt-V&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;iNline: Cmd-Alt-N&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;rename: Sh-F6&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;move method:  F6&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;change sig: Cmd-F6&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These 6 operations represent &amp;gt;80% of your minute-to-minute transforms. Ingrain them! (And don't forget Alt-Enter.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Not Buying Things Like a Pro</title>
      <link>https://oliz.io/blog/2019/not-buying-things-like-a-pro.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Feb 2019 10:24:42 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://oliz.io/blog/2019/not-buying-things-like-a-pro.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Anytime I catch myself not buying things, I put the money I was already willing to spend in a savings account. Requires introspection and discipline, though.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Originally posted on Twitter in reply to &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/farbodsaraf/status/1097239350759297030"&gt;Farbod Saraf&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Life lesson:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"If something cost $1,000, and it is on sale for $750, and then you decide to buy it, you did not save $250. You spent $750."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Softwerkskammmer Leipzig: Clean Code Session &amp;quot;TDD&amp;quot;</title>
      <link>https://oliz.io/blog/2019/swk-leipzig-clean-code-tdd-retro.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Sep 2019 23:57:48 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://oliz.io/blog/2019/swk-leipzig-clean-code-tdd-retro.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A little recap of what I learned/refreshed at the &lt;a href="https://www.meetup.com/de-DE/Softwerkskammer-Leipzig/events/264030290/"&gt;Softwerkskammer Leipzig meetup&lt;/a&gt;. We watched &lt;a href="https://cleancoders.com/video-details/clean-code-episode-6-p1"&gt;Robert "Uncle Bob" Martin's Clean Code Episode 6 Part 1&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://cleancoders.com/video-details/clean-code-episode-6-p2"&gt;part 2&lt;/a&gt;. Quotes by R. Martin if not noted otherwise:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="programming-wisdom"&gt;Programming wisdom&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Classes protect us from new types, data structures protect us from new functions&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;High debugging skill correlates with low productivity&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another word for testable is decoupled&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TDD is a prerequisite for professionalism&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Legacy code is code without tests (by Michael Feathers)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id="refactoring-techniques"&gt;Refactoring techniques&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Inline local/private functions before refactoring&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Extract code into inner class (quite commonly used by Uncle Bob)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do not use &lt;code&gt;StringBuffer&lt;/code&gt; in modern Java, the compiler is smart enough&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Multiply &lt;code&gt;if&lt;/code&gt;-statements&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Parametric loops&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="general-education"&gt;General education&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Theories how the moon came to be&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ignaz_Semmelweis"&gt;Ignaz Semmelweis&lt;/a&gt; not profiting from his &lt;a href="https://www.cs.utexas.edu/users/EWD/transcriptions/EWD10xx/EWD1036.html"&gt;radical novelty&lt;/a&gt; of hand washing during his lifetime&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Discipline are pre-made decisions&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Post-mortem: Global Game Jam 2019</title>
      <link>https://oliz.io/blog/2019/ggj19-post-mortem.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Feb 2019 22:24:09 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://oliz.io/blog/2019/ggj19-post-mortem.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This year's &lt;a href="https://globalgamejam.org/2019/games/home-48"&gt;Global Game Jam (GGJ)&lt;/a&gt; marked my fifth attendance in a row and was both my most refreshing and challenging jam so far.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="what-home-means-to-you"&gt;"what home means to you"&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The theme did not resonate with me.
The irony that I am on vacation, in my home town, on a weekend, participating in a GGJ, while my girlfriend waits at home, bogged my mind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had gameplay ideas, none of which seemed right considering the previous.
As a result I ditched my ideas and started from scratch. Already 17 hours into the jam.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="home-is"&gt;home is&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead I followed the advice of the first pair of keynote speakers to create a game that tries to invoke everyday or unusual feelings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have spent ca. 16 hours working on the game, 24 out of the 48 jam hours I spent at home with my girlfriend.
I consider this a great on-topic success! :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lessons learned to still deliver on time:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Phaser.js and GitHub Pages are still a winning combo for game jams!&lt;/strong&gt; I reused my &lt;a href="https://github.com/ooz/handshake"&gt;template from last year&lt;/a&gt;. Creating a game that runs in the browser also makes it really easy to do slight changes after game submission.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Plan!&lt;/strong&gt; I made exactly two paper sketches: 1. A list of all the 12 scenes and their respective topics. 2. A matrix of all assets I needed to create.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cut, then cut some more! Reuse like it is a triple-A game!&lt;/strong&gt; The asset matrix really helped here to show opportunities for reuse across scenes and cut assets that are not needed to convey the message. Unfortunately, this also meant skipping all sound (effects), which is usually great fun to create with fellow jammers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Focus on the story, keep gameplay minimal!&lt;/strong&gt; Adding more gameplay would have required way more iteration.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meta: This post was conceived on a paper notebook, then typed on a phone. All while on a train. The process was really refreshing and helped focusing on the content.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Today I Created my First Lego Instruction</title>
      <link>https://oliz.io/blog/2019/first-lego-instruction/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 14 Apr 2019 10:06:48 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://oliz.io/blog/2019/first-lego-instruction/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;"The Mosquito": &lt;a href="https://oliz.io/mocs/spaceships/the-mosquito/"&gt;https://oliz.io/mocs/spaceships/the-mosquito/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have 4-5 more spaceships/rockets to be digitalized, freeing up bricks.
&lt;a href="https://www.bricklink.com/v3/studio/download.page"&gt;BrickLink Studio&lt;/a&gt; is an amazing tool -- unfortunately, I did not even have a camera as a child... :D&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fixing the Middle Trackpoint Button on Old Thinkpad Keyboards</title>
      <link>https://oliz.io/blog/2019/fixing-middle-trackpoint-button/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 24 Feb 2019 21:00:02 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://oliz.io/blog/2019/fixing-middle-trackpoint-button/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;So far, I worked with two ThinkPads:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;T410, bought new in 2010. I replaced HDD/SSD, RAM, fan and keyboard.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;X220, bought refurbished in 2016 with an IPS screen. I cleaned it thoroughly, swapped SSD, RAM and keyboard.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The hardware is still suitable for modern-day software development work and I have yet to find a better typing experience on a laptop keyboard!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some time ago, I broke one bolt keeping the middle trackpoint button of the X220 keyboard in place. This resulted in an unpleasant scrolling experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When trying to remove the button to further investigate and fix the issue (no repair manual was consulted ☹), I broke the other bolt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Middle trackpoint button hinges" src="middle_trackpoint_button.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="isolation-tape-to-the-rescue"&gt;Isolation tape to the rescue!&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The solution was straightforward:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Push the hooks into the hook catchers, ensure the button rubber does not dislocate&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cut a strip of isolation tape in half&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Attach the tape to the button and wrap it around to the backside of the keyboard, firmly&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use the second half to secure the first half below the keyboard&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The result:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Final result" src="result.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;MacGyver score: &lt;strong&gt;6 out of 10&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Swiss Army Knife was used to (un-)screw the keyboard&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tape fixed the issue&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bubble gum was only chewed, not applied&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No evil plan was spoiled&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;☺&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On Software Minimalism</title>
      <link>https://oliz.io/blog/2020/on-software-minimalism.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Jun 2020 22:27:27 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://oliz.io/blog/2020/on-software-minimalism.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Recently, I iterated on &lt;a href="https://ooz.github.io/ggpy/"&gt;&lt;code&gt;gg.py&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; again, which ultimately led to the age-old question:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Why (re-inventing the wheel)?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="minimal-software"&gt;Minimal Software&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I like the idea of minimal software, just the amount of software needed to solve a problem, to fulfill a need. Typical characteristics of minimal software are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://suckless.org/philosophy/"&gt;Simple, elegant, usable, focused, reasonable and attainable&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Easier to understand&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Less prone to errors&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Less need for maintenance&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Less code (maybe)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I acknowledge that &lt;code&gt;gg.py&lt;/code&gt; could have also been realized in shell using the &lt;a href="https://busybox.net/"&gt;BusyBox set of UNIX utilities&lt;/a&gt;.
Regardless, I enjoy working with Python and having a pet project keeps my language skills and tool chain sharp.
Software minimalism followed to the extreme would consider Python and anything written in it as "bloat" and not minimal. On a second look, the above traits of minimal software seem to be rather &lt;em&gt;means goals&lt;/em&gt; than end goals. Extrapolated, I see one over-arching objective:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;To spend less time with software!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="standard-software-and-innovation"&gt;Standard Software and Innovation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Spending less time with software frees you up to spend more time outside, off the computer, with friends and family. Or to focus on the business side of things. Shell one-liners and clever single-file programs may be one approach, but for plenty of people the use of &lt;em&gt;standard software&lt;/em&gt; is exactly that:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The majority of people use it&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The majority of people has good-enough understanding of its benefits and constraints&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Someone else develops, maintains and supports it&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Standard software is not necessarily user-facing software, but also common software libraries, frameworks, programming languages, open-source or industry standards.
One downside of using standard software is the loss of competitive advantage stemming from superior tools and craft. Then, &lt;a href="http://www.paulgraham.com/avg.html"&gt;beating the averages&lt;/a&gt; and innovation are not a matter of technology, but of appropriate and repeated creative application valuing the zeitgeist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="in-perspective"&gt;In Perspective&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This cannot be an argument for minimal, custom-built software, nor standard software. Neither seems to grant an advantage inherently, so a healthy dose of pragmatism is required when developing or utilizing software in a competitive space.
Shifting the point of view, someone's minimal software might be someone else's standard software (e.g. UNIX utilities leveraged by an advanced user) and someone's standard software might be considered "overkill" by minimalists (e.g. WYSIWYG word processors for writing plain text).
At the end of the day, users minding their respective computer skills could still all agree that their preferred software tool enables them &lt;em&gt;to spend less time&lt;/em&gt; with the computer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This turns the question &lt;em&gt;"does this software enable me to spend more quality time off (or on) the machine?"&lt;/em&gt; into a metric for gauging software value.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Does this social network enrich my life or is it just artificially keeping me hooked to my phone for corporate profits?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Does this computer game offer quality experience and immersion or is it just a paint over grind to grow &lt;a href="https://www.investopedia.com/terms/m/monthly-active-user-mau.asp"&gt;MAU&lt;/a&gt;?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Does this software tool enable me to get more things done and turn off the computer earlier?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As for &lt;code&gt;gg.py&lt;/code&gt;, it covers my static site generator needs. Growing with it and having full creative expression are their own rewards. ☺&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On Fact Checks</title>
      <link>https://oliz.io/blog/2020/on-fact-checks.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Oct 2020 17:30:27 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://oliz.io/blog/2020/on-fact-checks.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Isn't it ironic after decades of framing and "appeal to emotion" by media and PR, those techniques are now so universally used that the same organisations losing control are urged to provide "fact checks"? 😅&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Software Development Talks Binge and Random Wisdom</title>
      <link>https://oliz.io/blog/2020/dev-talk-binge-random-wisdom/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Nov 2020 22:32:10 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://oliz.io/blog/2020/dev-talk-binge-random-wisdom/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;While researching for &lt;a href="../economics-of-software-design/"&gt;the previous blog post&lt;/a&gt;, I stumbled upon another &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=WSes_PexXcA"&gt;J. B. Rainsberger talk&lt;/a&gt; on how accidental complications sabotage estimations, which is also excellent on a meta level since he hits his talk duration estimate on the second!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From there on the YouTube algorithm dragged me further into the maze...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="overwatch-gameplay-architecture-and-netcode"&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=W3aieHjyNvw"&gt;Overwatch Gameplay Architecture and Netcode&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How Overwatch implemented Entity Component System (ECS) as an architecture:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Components have no functions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Systems have no state&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Systems cannot call other systems&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some more:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Game runs at fixed frame rate, sends a sliding window (ring buffer) of input to mitigate UDP packet loss&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The input buffer size is dynamic: the higher the latency, the bigger the buffer&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Entire simulation is deterministic, can be interpolated and re-winded&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you take away one lesson from this talk let it be this: behaviors are much less complex if they are expressed in a single callsite, in which all major behavioral sideeffects are localized to that callsite.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id="networking-scripted-weapons-and-abilities-in-overwatch"&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ScyZjcjTlA4"&gt;Networking Scripted Weapons and Abilities in Overwatch&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;"Statescript", custom scripting language for gameplay&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Key game design insight: "awesome moves" (specials) block re-winding, so significant player abilities/cooldowns are not rolled back&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Overall not as interesting as the first talk, but has some nice diagrams for the netcode and prediction:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Predicted StatescriptPacket" src="predicted_packet.png" /&gt;
&lt;img alt="Mispredicted StatescriptPacket" src="mispredicted_packet.png" /&gt;
(screenshots from the talk linked above)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="roguelike-development"&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=jviNpRGuCIU"&gt;Roguelike Development&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(from the &lt;a href="https://www.gridsagegames.com/cogmind/"&gt;Cogmind&lt;/a&gt; developer)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Develop the critical path first, focus on the core mechanic, release early and often, blog&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Recommends to practice making smaller roguelikes first, e.g. 7-day roguelikes (7DRL)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/roguelikedev/"&gt;roguelike development reddit&lt;/a&gt; for plenty of resources, discussion and help&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mind accessibility, e.g. Cogmind players prefer tileset graphics and mouse controls&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;All in all, nice overview of plenty of roguelike themes, mechanics and layouts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here the binge ended, but more happened since the last blog post:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="softwerkskammmer-leipzig-working-from-home-special"&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.meetup.com/de-DE/LE-software-craft-community/events/273864764/"&gt;Softwerkskammmer Leipzig: Working From Home Special&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lean Coffee on remote work mostly due to Corona. When talking about "overcommunicating", we recalled documentation essentials:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;URL&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Author&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Timestamp, versioning&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Searchable&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="attention-economy"&gt;&lt;a href="https://aeon.co/videos/a-handful-of-executives-control-the-attention-economy-time-for-attentive-resistance"&gt;Attention Economy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A nice video on the attention economy, social media selling attention of their users.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[...] a wealth of information creates a poverty of attention [...]
-- Herbert A. Simon, 1971&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id="further-links"&gt;Further Links&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/huge-success/sanic/"&gt;Python Sanic: a web app framework&lt;/a&gt; which looks like an evolution of &lt;a href="https://palletsprojects.com/p/flask/"&gt;Flask&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://docs.fedoraproject.org/en-US/quick-docs/understanding-and-administering-systemd/index.html"&gt;systemd: basics (Fedora documentation)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.raspberrypi.org/documentation/linux/usage/systemd.md"&gt;systemd: basic service template for Raspberry Pi&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.raspberrypi.org/documentation/linux/usage/cron.md"&gt;cron reference (Raspberry Pi documentation)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://briarproject.org"&gt;https://briarproject.org&lt;/a&gt; -- encrypted P2P messaging and forums, as an alternative to Telegram, WhatsApp and Threema&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Corona Sky</title>
      <link>https://oliz.io/blog/2020/corona-sky/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 23 Aug 2020 15:10:25 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://oliz.io/blog/2020/corona-sky/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Despite all the negative effects of Corona, I prefer to appreciate the novel experiences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="corona-skies"&gt;Corona skies&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Corona Sky" src="corona-sky.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The European airspace is one of the most utilized on earth.
Thus it is rare to look up the sky and not see any condensation trails.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, living in a city with a nearby airport, we have &lt;em&gt;Corona skies&lt;/em&gt;, which I would define as:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The natural sky either clouded or cloudless without any signs of human flight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Corona Sky panorama" src="corona-sky_pano.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="dystopian-malls"&gt;Dystopian malls&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whenever getting supplies, there are recorded public announcements playing.
The content always boils down to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mind the &lt;em&gt;government&lt;/em&gt; Corona &lt;em&gt;laws&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Stay &lt;em&gt;safe and healthy&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Enjoy and &lt;em&gt;keep shopping&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which perfectly aligns with any dystopian story ever.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Software Craft Community @DATEV: The Economics of Software Design / Manufacturing Slack by J. B. Rainsberger</title>
      <link>https://oliz.io/blog/2020/economics-of-software-design/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Oct 2020 20:49:10 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://oliz.io/blog/2020/economics-of-software-design/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On Oct 1st 2020 &lt;a href="https://ti.to/scc-datev/jbrains/en"&gt;DATEV hosted an online meetup&lt;/a&gt; with &lt;a href="https://www.jbrains.ca"&gt;J. B. Rainsberger&lt;/a&gt; ("JBR" for the rest of the post) condensing two of his workshops/talks into 1.5 hours.
While I missed the first ten minutes of the talk (first argument?), the rest was still very interesting and spot-on!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="cost-of-changing-software"&gt;Cost of Changing Software&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;JBR started with how to communicate the benefit of good software development practices to managers and co-workers. To accountants, he'd recommend the goal of evolutionary design as:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"Reduce the volatility in the marginal cost of features" - JBR&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;which basically means that good practices make software development cost more predictable, easier to account for.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He illustrated this with two exponential functions (all three diagrams drawn by JBR, shot&amp;amp;cropped by me). In Fig. 1:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Red curve describing ad-hoc design, spaghetti code, few/no tests, no refactoring etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Green curve following good software development practices like agile, evolutionary design, TDD etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;JBR acknowledged that software development cost always follows exponential functions.
He motivated the base of the red exponential function being &lt;em&gt;e&lt;/em&gt; (Euler's number) with technical debt accumulating like compound interest. Good practices result in a lower base and higher initial cost.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Two exponential functions for software development cost" src="00_two_functions.png" /&gt;
[Fig. 1: cost of software development practices (green good, red poor).]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There's a point in time where the accumulated costs (integrals) of both approaches are equal (at &lt;em&gt;t0&lt;/em&gt;). Past this point, the project following evolutionary design becomes cheaper.
&lt;img alt="Equal cost of both approaches at t0" src="01_t0_equal_cost.png" /&gt;
[Fig. 2: t0, time of equal project cost.]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At some further point in time, &lt;em&gt;project heat death&lt;/em&gt; is reached: Change becomes too expensive and a rewrite is favored (Fig. 3). The goal of any good development practice should be&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;to have &lt;em&gt;t0&lt;/em&gt; as early as possible and&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;to delay project heat death as long as possible.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Project heat death" src="02_project_heat_death.png" /&gt;
[Fig. 3: project heat death occurs when cost of change is unreasonably high.]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the contrary, spaghetti software development may still be favored by managers if they gamble on the project dying before &lt;em&gt;t0&lt;/em&gt;. Then the big question is: Do managers account for this consciously?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="from-waterfall-to-tdd-to-lean-startup"&gt;From Waterfall to TDD to Lean Startup&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The last part was about transforming any waterfall-ish development process into the ideal &lt;em&gt;lean startup&lt;/em&gt; (LS) by introducing feedback loops, repeatedly cutting feedback loops in half and as a result moving process throughput from micro-level "working code" to organization-level "money/revenue". JBR referred to foundations in queuing theory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Citing the &lt;a href="http://www-scf.usc.edu/~csci201/lectures/Lecture11/royce1970.pdf"&gt;infamous and greatly misunderstood W. W. Royce paper from 1970&lt;/a&gt;, JBR reminded the audience, that the Waterfall model was said to only ever work for straight-forward projects. Even in the original concept, it was described as risky and prone to failures (p. 2, s. 1).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To improve the Waterfall concept of&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="highlight"&gt;&lt;code&gt;R --v               # Research / Requirements / Analysis
   D --v            # Design
       C --v        # Code
           T --v    # Test
               M    # Maintenance / Ops&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One could first introduce the feedback loop of test-first programming (TFP) iterating between code and tests. The throughput of this feedback loop is working code. The Waterfall then becomes&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="highlight"&gt;&lt;code&gt;R --v
   D --v
       TFP --v
             M&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Iterating between design and TFP using refactoring is essentially test-driven development (TDD), producing well-designed and working code. This replaces another part of the Waterfall&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="highlight"&gt;&lt;code&gt;R --v
    TDD --v
          M&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Continuing the pattern and looping between requirement analysis and TDD, the process becomes behavior-driven development (BDD). The throughput will be well-designed, working code which reflects business needs. JBR suggested "talk to me in examples" to inquire requirements of stakeholders. The Waterfall shrinks to a puddle:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="highlight"&gt;&lt;code&gt;BDD --v
      M&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looping feedback between BDD and maintenance/operations results in continuous delivery (CD). Eventually the throughput becomes real value: money/revenue. Further shortening the feedback cycles, CD becomes the ideal LS ("cash in my pockets sooner" - JBR).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="highlight"&gt;&lt;code&gt;CD --shorter cycles--&amp;gt; LS&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Joy of Lego as an Adult</title>
      <link>https://oliz.io/blog/2017/joy-of-lego.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 08 Jan 2017 17:51:06 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://oliz.io/blog/2017/joy-of-lego.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I think most people having access to Lego in their childhood can relate to this: At some point you have built it all, you get your first computer and suddenly you are wondering why you are still bringing this box of colorful bricks everytime you relocate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2016 I bought my first Lego set after a long hiatus. &lt;a href="https://shop.lego.com/de-DE/WALL-E-21303"&gt;WALL-E&lt;/a&gt; set me back 50 € (and another 50 € for the motors - yes, I was ambitious).
They say you should rather invest in experiences instead of &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=MvgN5gCuLac"&gt;stuff&lt;/a&gt;. I wholeheartedly agree!
Those 50 € did not buy me a box of bricks. They bought me 1.5 hours of pure joy: How the rounded pieces fit into the square ones, how vertical accents spanned multiple horizontal layers, how rubber parts interact with ABS plastic, how known bricks locked with new design elements etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eventually I bought other sets, completely redesigned the rear of my WALL-E to support a "battery backpack" alongside motors and the infrared control, created a tablet/smartphone stand, envisioned a drone carrier from simple design bricks, built multiple Pokemon within the constraints of one set and enjoyed all the possibilities with the new design and joint/hinge elements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the next posts I will write about:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="lego-architecture-studio2drone-carrier.html"&gt;the drone carrier and tablet/smartphone stand&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="building-pokemon-from-15-euro-sets.html"&gt;my "Pokemon challenge"&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Enjoy!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How to assign the Logitech MX518 extra buttons under Ubuntu 16.04</title>
      <link>https://oliz.io/blog/2017/mx518-ubuntu.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Feb 2017 10:26:46 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://oliz.io/blog/2017/mx518-ubuntu.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Once a while™ I like to play strategy or MMO games on PC.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back in 2006 I bought the fantastic Logitech MX518 gaming mouse and have been using it ever since.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Logitech MX518 gaming mouse" src="https://images-na.ssl-images-amazon.com/images/I/91YmmYMH40L._SL1500_.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(&lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/Logitech-910-000616-MX518-Optical-Gaming/dp/B0015R8M7U"&gt;Image source: Amazon&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you can see in the picture the mouse sports extra buttons that are handy when assigned properly in games.
This works just fine under Windows with the tools Logitech provides.
Before Ubuntu switched to &lt;code&gt;systemd&lt;/code&gt; there was a tool named &lt;a href="https://launchpad.net/btnx"&gt;&lt;code&gt;btnx&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; that enabled me to assign keyboard keys to mouse buttons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It just worked!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the adaption of &lt;code&gt;systemd&lt;/code&gt; in Ubuntu (16.04 was my first version with systemd, since I only use LTS versions), &lt;code&gt;btnx&lt;/code&gt; stopped working since it relied on &lt;code&gt;init.d&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So here is how I got it to work with &lt;code&gt;systemd&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Install lomoco:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="highlight"&gt;&lt;code class="language-bash"&gt;sudo apt install lomoco&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Configure lomoco and set the mouse resolution to 1200, otherwise the button reassignment is not possible:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="highlight"&gt;&lt;code class="language-bash"&gt;sudo vim /etc/default/lomoco&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The resulting file should look like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="highlight"&gt;&lt;code&gt;# Configuration file for lomoco
# see `man lomoco` for details

# Define which resolution should be used
# Values:      800,400,1200,1600
LOGITECH_MOUSE_RESOLUTION=1200

# Whether to disable SmartScroll/Cruise Control. Defaults to yes if not set.
# Values:      yes,no
LOGITECH_MOUSE_DISABLE_CC=&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Install the outdated packages &lt;a href="https://launchpad.net/btnx-config/"&gt;btnx-config&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://launchpad.net/btnx"&gt;btnx&lt;/a&gt; (in this order).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Restart Ubuntu.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Create the btnx.service for systemd (I still think one of those files is redundant, I did not dive that deep into systemd yet):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Content of the btnx.service file:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="highlight"&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Unit]
Description=Btnx
Documentation=https://ooz.github.io
After=graphical.target

[Service]
Type=simple
ExecStart=/usr/sbin/btnx
PIDFile=/var/run/btnx.pid
Restart=on-abort&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Place it at the following locations:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="highlight"&gt;&lt;code class="language-bash"&gt;sudo cp btnx.service /etc/systemd/system/
sudo cp btnx.service /etc/systemd/system/graphical.target.wants/&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Start the btnx.service:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="highlight"&gt;&lt;code class="language-bash"&gt;sudo systemctl start btnx.service&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can verify whether the service has launched with the following command:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="highlight"&gt;&lt;code class="language-bash"&gt;systemctl status btnx.service&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Launch btnx-config and configure your mouse!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="highlight"&gt;&lt;code class="language-bash"&gt;sudo btnx-config&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;"Detect mouse &amp;amp; buttons"&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Press every mouse button once&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Switch tab, select mouse button, enable keyboard overwrite, assign keyboard key to mouse button&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Restart Ubuntu and you are done!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Building Pokemon from 15 to 18 Euro Lego Sets</title>
      <link>https://oliz.io/blog/2017/building-pokemon-from-15-euro-sets.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 08 Jan 2017 23:44:24 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://oliz.io/blog/2017/building-pokemon-from-15-euro-sets.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In late 2016 I bought the Lego set "Red Creatures", which sadly is not available anymore.
I always liked dragons, so I had to get and build it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wandering around in the Lego store I wondered why there is no Pokemon Lego yet.
I mean they have made so many deals: Star Wars, Minecraft, Marvel, DC, ... and Pokemon is still targeted mostly at children. So why not join forces?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, back in 1999 I had built a Blastoise and a Pikachu from simple bricks.
Sadly I did not have any camera at that time (not counting the 14336 pixel (!) Game Boy Camera) to record my achievement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I had this 15 € "Red Creatures" set, another 15 € set with a dog and a duck (lots of joint and hinge elements - I love those!)
But it was not until I bought the relatively new green dinosaur set, I certified just by looking at the box: Yep, this should make a really nice &lt;strong&gt;Venusaur&lt;/strong&gt; (ger.: Bisaflor)! And this time I have a smartphone camera:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Lego Venusaur" src="lego_bisaflor.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Real Venusaur" src="http://www.pokewiki.de/images/1/19/Sugimori_003.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(&lt;a href="http://www.pokewiki.de/Datei:Sugimori_003.png"&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;, see license, ™ &amp;amp; © Nintendo)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Close enough! Overall it was straight-forward to build and I had lots of fun!
By the way, this is the package of the original set:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Lego Dinosaur" src="/blog/ext_img/2017/lego_dinosaur.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(&lt;a href="https://shop.lego.com/de-DE/Dinosaurier-31058"&gt;Source of the screenshot&lt;/a&gt;, © LEGO Group)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Highly motivated I had to build my all-time favorite: &lt;strong&gt;Charizard&lt;/strong&gt; (ger.: Glurak)!
I kept the trunk from the "Red Creatures" model, removed the black spikes made from design elements, reduced the head size and simplified legs, arms, tail as well as wings. In my opinion this is even a better, more play-able dragon than the original model (the original wings are way too complicated and hinder you when you actually want to &lt;em&gt;use&lt;/em&gt; the model).
This is the result:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Lego Charizard" src="lego_glurak.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Real Charizard" src="http://www.pokewiki.de/images/9/96/Sugimori_006.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(&lt;a href="http://www.pokewiki.de/Datei:Sugimori_006.png"&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;, see license, ™ &amp;amp; © Nintendo)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;FEUER! YEAH!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(The original set again, just for reference:)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Lego Red Creatures" src="/blog/ext_img/2017/lego_rote_kreaturen.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(&lt;a href="https://shop.lego.com/de-DE/Rote-Kreaturen-31032"&gt;Source of the screenshot&lt;/a&gt;, © LEGO Group)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next day I was on a mission: Find a set to build the third starter Pokemon, &lt;strong&gt;Blastoise&lt;/strong&gt; (ger.: Turtok)!
So I looked for more cheap 3-in-1 Lego sets containing some blue bricks. There it was:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Lego Robot" src="/blog/ext_img/2017/lego_robot.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(&lt;a href="https://shop.lego.com/de-DE/Forschungsroboter-31062"&gt;Source of the screenshot&lt;/a&gt;, © LEGO Group)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just looking at the set, I knew it would be a challenge to build Blastoise. The more so, I was pleased with the result:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Lego Blastoise" src="lego_turtok.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But it has most features of the real Blastoise like movable cannons!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Real Blastoise" src="http://www.pokewiki.de/images/9/9a/Sugimori_009.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(&lt;a href="http://www.pokewiki.de/Datei:Sugimori_009.png"&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;, see license, ™ &amp;amp; © Nintendo)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being in a flow state I created another Pokemon: &lt;strong&gt;Pidgeot&lt;/strong&gt; (ger.: Tauboss)!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Real Pidgeot" src="http://pokewiki.de/images/2/23/Sugimori_018.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(&lt;a href="http://pokewiki.de/Datei:Sugimori_018.png"&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;, see license, ™ &amp;amp; © Nintendo)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Lego Pidgeot" src="lego_tauboss.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From this set:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Lego Park Animals" src="/blog/ext_img/2017/lego_park_animals.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(&lt;a href="https://www.lego.com/de-de/creator/products/park-animals-31044"&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;, © LEGO Group)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Technically one should be able to build any brown-whitish Pokemon from this set.
Feel free to email me or drop a comment, if you have any ideas or suggestions!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="what-to-take-home"&gt;What to Take Home&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;So why should anyone bother building Pokemon?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Well, this "exercise" could be seen as a training for the following skills:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Evaluation + estimation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Look at a package and try to guess which Pokemon you can build&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Staying within budget / limits&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
You can only use the bricks being part of one less-than-20-€-set&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstraction + reduction&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Extract the essential features of a Pokemon and translate them to the Lego design&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Convert curl commands to Python, JavaScript fetch, Go, PHP and more</title>
      <link>https://oliz.io/blog/2017/convert-curl-commands.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Sep 2017 21:29:19 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://oliz.io/blog/2017/convert-curl-commands.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://curl.trillworks.com"&gt;https://curl.trillworks.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hello World, Hello New Blog!</title>
      <link>https://oliz.io/blog/2017/hello.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 07 Jan 2017 13:37:42 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://oliz.io/blog/2017/hello.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I'm Oliver and this is my personal blog about:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Time&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
    It's sometimes in the name. Also it is the only resource there is and we are chronically out of it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Life&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
    Tied closely to 1.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Design&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
    What I like, what I dislike, what I learned. This will probably involve some Lego.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Technology and Software Engineering&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
    That is what I do for a living.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Zen&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
    Starts with Z, too.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This post will serve me as a reference, so expect to see weird things below this line:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Tables&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;work&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th align="right"&gt;just&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;fine&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;for&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;real&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;yep&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;yeah.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;pre class="highlight"&gt;&lt;code class="language-python"&gt;def python():
    return "does as well!"&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let there be...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;another
code
block
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Various &lt;code&gt;inline&lt;/code&gt; &lt;em&gt;highlighting&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;works&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;del&gt;too&lt;/del&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is so smart.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul class="task-list"&gt;
&lt;li class="task-list-item"&gt;&lt;input type="checkbox" disabled/&gt; Checklists&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li class="task-list-item"&gt;&lt;input type="checkbox" disabled checked/&gt; work!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Images with alt work!" src="/blog/static/owl.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="markdown-extensions"&gt;Markdown Extensions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;dl&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Definition List&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;is defined here.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Other List&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;is defined here.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;
&lt;h2 id="abbreviations"&gt;Abbreviations&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Hyper Text Markup Language"&gt;HTML&lt;/abbr&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="footnotes1"&gt;Footnotes&lt;sup id="fnref:1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other footnote &lt;sup id="fnref:blub"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:blub"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First footnote&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:1" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:blub"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Blub footnote&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:blub" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>High-performance Web Server for Rapid Development of Web Apps</title>
      <link>https://oliz.io/blog/2017/rapid-asm-web-app-dev.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Apr 2017 13:37:49 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://oliz.io/blog/2017/rapid-asm-web-app-dev.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;...in Assembler: &lt;a href="https://2ton.com.au/rwasa/"&gt;https://2ton.com.au/rwasa/&lt;/a&gt; ;)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Naming Schemes</title>
      <link>https://oliz.io/blog/2017/naming-schemes.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Oct 2017 21:22:07 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://oliz.io/blog/2017/naming-schemes.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A good naming scheme is scalable, unique, and easy to remember. The purpose of these naming schemes is to name networked servers, wireless access points or client computers, but it can also be used to name projects, products, variables, streets, pets, kids, or any other project where unique names and rememberable names are required.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://namingschemes.com"&gt;https://namingschemes.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Serverless in One Slide</title>
      <link>https://oliz.io/blog/2017/serverless-in-one-slide.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Apr 2017 00:06:33 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://oliz.io/blog/2017/serverless-in-one-slide.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;short running functions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;compute containers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;stateless&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;3rd-party managed&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;event-triggered&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/coderbyheart/status/847522021990895621"&gt;https://twitter.com/coderbyheart/status/847522021990895621&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Survivorship Bias</title>
      <link>https://oliz.io/blog/2017/survivorship-bias.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 03 Jun 2017 13:37:53 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://oliz.io/blog/2017/survivorship-bias.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Survivorship_bias#In_the_military"&gt;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Survivorship_bias#In_the_military&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Python Anti-Patterns</title>
      <link>https://oliz.io/blog/2017/python-anti-patterns.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Nov 2017 21:03:08 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://oliz.io/blog/2017/python-anti-patterns.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://lignos.org/py_antipatterns/"&gt;https://lignos.org/py_antipatterns/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>So My Girlfriend Ordered Lego Architecture Studio...</title>
      <link>https://oliz.io/blog/2017/lego-architecture-studio2drone-carrier.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 08 Jan 2017 22:57:58 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://oliz.io/blog/2017/lego-architecture-studio2drone-carrier.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;...and I could not resist building a drone carrier!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Lego Drone Carrier - Pew! Pew!" src="lego_drone_carrier.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At first I was sceptical: The set is overpriced, yielding only white and transparent bricks, no special functional parts (e.g. joints/hinges) etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My better half ordered the set anyway and I found those limits inspiring. While she built a house, I wanted something &lt;em&gt;practical&lt;/em&gt;. Like a drone carrier for world domination, you know?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The bricks also make a nice tablet stand:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Tablet/smartphone stand made from Lego" src="lego_tablet_stand.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;;)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Brackets, Parentheses, Braces</title>
      <link>https://oliz.io/blog/2017/brackets-parentheses-braces.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Nov 2017 21:09:22 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://oliz.io/blog/2017/brackets-parentheses-braces.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;pre class="highlight"&gt;&lt;code&gt;[] brackets (US), square brackets
() parentheses, brackets (non-US English), round brackets
&amp;lt;&amp;gt; angle brackets
{} curly braces (US), curly brackets&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Parenthesis is the singular of parentheses (short: parens)! ;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/gfixler/status/926950212760870913"&gt;https://twitter.com/gfixler/status/926950212760870913&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bracket"&gt;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bracket&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Password Rules</title>
      <link>https://oliz.io/blog/2017/password-rules.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 19 Mar 2017 00:39:24 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://oliz.io/blog/2017/password-rules.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://blog.codinghorror.com/password-rules-are-bullshit/"&gt;https://blog.codinghorror.com/password-rules-are-bullshit/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TL;DR:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Minimum length&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reasonable maximum length&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Be aware of Unicode&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Think like a user&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How to not do it: &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/AaronToponce/status/988761412464857088"&gt;https://twitter.com/AaronToponce/status/988761412464857088&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How to configure Xmonad for Ubuntu</title>
      <link>https://oliz.io/blog/2017/xmonad-ubuntu.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Apr 2017 21:20:32 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://oliz.io/blog/2017/xmonad-ubuntu.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In the last six months I must have set up my default Ubuntu 16.04 + Xmonad desktop environment on like four or more machines.
The goal looks like this (I like to have the top bar for status and widgets):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Ubuntu and Xmonad" src="ubuntu_xmonad.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is a small guide for future reference:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="step-by-step-guide"&gt;Step-by-step Guide&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Install the Xmonad package:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="highlight"&gt;&lt;code class="language-bash"&gt;sudo apt install xmonad&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point you can already select an Xmonad session at the login screen.
But this is not recommended.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So additionally you should install the &lt;a href="https://github.com/Gekkio/gnome-session-xmonad"&gt;&lt;code&gt;gnome-session-xmonad&lt;/code&gt; package&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="highlight"&gt;&lt;code class="language-bash"&gt;sudo add-apt-repository ppa:gekkio/xmonad
sudo apt-get update
sudo apt-get install gnome-session-xmonad&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Configure Xmonad. The Xmonad configuration is written in Haskell. If you are uncertain or need something working to start from, you are free to take &lt;a href="https://github.com/ooz/olli/blob/master/.xmonad/xmonad.hs"&gt;my configuration&lt;/a&gt;. Place it here: &lt;code&gt;~/.xmonad/xmonad.hs&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Relog and choose the &lt;strong&gt;GNOME + XMonad&lt;/strong&gt; session at the login screen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you dislike the bottom panel (like I do, see above screenshot), you can disable it with:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="highlight"&gt;&lt;code&gt;dconf write /org/gnome/gnome-panel/layout/toplevel-id-list "['top-panel']"
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To redisplay it, execute:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="highlight"&gt;&lt;code&gt;dconf write /org/gnome/gnome-panel/layout/toplevel-id-list "['top-panel','bottom-panel']"&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Have fun!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="update-2021-09-14"&gt;Update 2021-09-14&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The above guide also works for Ubuntu 18.04 and 20.04.
However, for version 20.04 further tweaks are needed:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fix layout switch (Super+Space):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The shortcut is claimed by GNOME and needs to be disabled in "Settings &amp;gt; Keyboard Shortcuts &amp;gt; Switch to next input source"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remove the Terminal title bar:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="highlight"&gt;&lt;code&gt;sudo apt install gnome-shell-extension-pixelsaver
gnome-extensions enable pixel-saver@deadalnix.me
gsettings set org.gnome.Terminal.Legacy.Settings headerbar false&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href="https://askubuntu.com/questions/1230157/how-to-remove-title-bar-from-terminal-on-the-new-ubuntu-20-04"&gt;https://askubuntu.com/questions/1230157/how-to-remove-title-bar-from-terminal-on-the-new-ubuntu-20-04&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hide desktop icons:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Inspired by: &lt;a href="https://askubuntu.com/questions/1230877/how-to-remove-home-folder-icon-from-desktop-in-ubuntu-20-04"&gt;https://askubuntu.com/questions/1230877/how-to-remove-home-folder-icon-from-desktop-in-ubuntu-20-04&lt;/a&gt; (the keys however don't work for &lt;code&gt;GNOME + XMonad&lt;/code&gt; session). Correct key:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="highlight"&gt;&lt;code&gt;gsettings set org.gnome.gnome-flashback.desktop show-icons false&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dark theme:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's called 'Yaru-dark' (default is 'Yaru', a light theme) and can be set under &lt;code&gt;org.gnome.desktop.interface.gtk-theme&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chromium snap context menu&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For me, context menu (e.g. right click on links) didn't work with the new Chromium snap.
The solution is to &lt;a href="https://askubuntu.com/questions/1315914/chrome-chromium-context-menu-lag"&gt;disable hardware accerlation&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Crafting a Durable Personal Kanban Board</title>
      <link>https://oliz.io/blog/2017/crafting-a-durable-personal-kanban-board/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Oct 2017 00:40:20 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://oliz.io/blog/2017/crafting-a-durable-personal-kanban-board/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;One of my highlights at this year's &lt;a href="https://www.socrates-conference.de/"&gt;SoCraTes in Soltau&lt;/a&gt; was a session about Personal Kanban hosted by &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/rradczewski/"&gt;Raimo&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/janernsting/"&gt;Jan&lt;/a&gt;.
They shared their experiences, practises and highlighted the advantages of a physical board.
We even got provided material to build our own Personal Kanban boards. Mine looked like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Opened Personal Kanban board from SoCraTes 2017" src="pkanban_paper_open.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Front cover of my Personal Kanban board from SoCraTes 2017" src="pkanban_paper_front.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While it was really neat that you could start using it right away, I felt the need to have a more durable board to really start utilizing it.
The solution was simple:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="more-plastic"&gt;&lt;a href="https://youtu.be/7W33HRc1A6c?t=350"&gt;MORE PLASTIC!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the session I already had the idea, that my old plastic clipboard would be the perfect board material. The plastic is really smooth and sticky notes just, well, &lt;em&gt;stick&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This week I made it to a stationery shop in Hamburg and bought some more transparent and black clipboards:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Clipboard base material" src="pkanban_clipboards.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With some skill, tools and the right amount of force you can remove the clipboard part:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Plastic boards without clip" src="pkanban_remove_clip.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It goes faster after the second bolt, since you know how much force you can apply without damaging the plastic board. Still I cracked one of the transparent boards slightly. Be careful!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Waste" src="pkanban_waste.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="tools-used"&gt;Tools used&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Used tools" src="pkanban_tools.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Adhesive tape" src="pkanban_krepp.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A flat screwdriver to pry open the bolts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A strong pincer to destroy and remove the bolts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Adhesive tape to join 2 boards&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Scissors to cut the tape&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A ruler for drawing lines&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Black / white permanent markers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="actually-composing-the-board"&gt;Actually composing the board&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The hard part is over, the rest is just joining and labeling the board.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you put two of those boards back to back, you get a laptop-ish clamshell design. You need to keep a gap when joining the two boards, so they stay foldable:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Mind the gap" src="pkanban_fold.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After drawing the sections and labels:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Black Personal Kanban board with white ink" src="pkanban_transparent_open.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="result"&gt;Result&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My girlfriend liked the board so much, I needed to craft an additional one:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Black Personal Kanban board with white ink" src="pkanban_black_board_open.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Applying some stickers lying around (I do not like putting them on laptops):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Resulting Personal Kanban boards" src="pkanban_result.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Costs:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Money: 9.60 € for 2 plastic clipboards, 4.30 € for a new adhesive tape reel, 7.50 € for the two (black + white) permanent markers. So ca. 30 € for two Personal Kanban boards, ca. 11 € per board if you consider the amount of tape / ink used.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Time: ca. 40 minutes for the transparent board with black permanent marker (incl. learning how to remove the board clips), ca. 1 hour for the black board with white permanent marker (be careful with the ink, it can get really messy!)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, the best result is that I actually apply Personal Kanban now! :)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>B. Franklin: &amp;quot;Either write something worth reading or do something worth writing.&amp;quot;</title>
      <link>https://oliz.io/blog/2016/benjamin-franklin.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Apr 2016 13:37:41 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://oliz.io/blog/2016/benjamin-franklin.html</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>K. Reitz: &amp;quot;Attention is the only currency we have in life. Thanks for gifting me yours.&amp;quot;</title>
      <link>https://oliz.io/blog/2016/kenneth-reitz-attention.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Apr 2016 13:37:48 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://oliz.io/blog/2016/kenneth-reitz-attention.html</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How TED Talks Work</title>
      <link>https://oliz.io/blog/2016/how-ted-talks-work.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Sep 2016 00:34:17 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://oliz.io/blog/2016/how-ted-talks-work.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dr._Fox_effect"&gt;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dr._Fox_effect&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Via: &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/mr_scientism/status/777938499999830017"&gt;https://twitter.com/mr_scientism/status/777938499999830017&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lean: OSS Theorem Prover</title>
      <link>https://oliz.io/blog/2016/lean-theorem-prover.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Aug 2016 13:37:37 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://oliz.io/blog/2016/lean-theorem-prover.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://leanprover.github.io/about/"&gt;https://leanprover.github.io/about/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Just English Things</title>
      <link>https://oliz.io/blog/2016/english-things.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 24 Apr 2016 00:27:27 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://oliz.io/blog/2016/english-things.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes, English can be weird.
It can be understood through tough thorough thought, though.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/olamy/status/723732629674041345"&gt;https://twitter.com/olamy/status/723732629674041345&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
