<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Oli Z.</title>
    <link>https://oliz.io/blog</link>
    <description></description>
    <generator>Good Generator.py -- ggpy -- https://oliz.io/ggpy</generator>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 16 Apr 2022 06:55:12 -0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://oliz.io/blog/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Mastering the Keyboard, the Mouse and Any Input Method or Tool, Really</title>
      <link>https://oliz.io/blog/2022/mastering-the-keyboard/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Mar 2022 09:13:03 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://oliz.io/blog/2022/mastering-the-keyboard/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Hey,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://oliz.io/blog/2022/on-mastery.html"&gt;As you may have read, I recently wrote about mastery.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a lifelong keyboard warrior, I have always appreciated the efficiency, precision and direct access of one of my best tools: The Keyboard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, today I'm writing about that. Yeah, yeah, of course, I use a mouse, too. But that's a different topic for someone else, really.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-keys"&gt;The Keys&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Images go long way, they say. I'm not a good photographer by any means, but I sincerely hope, you get the idea:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Some input methods" src="tools.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="my-reading-of-the-keys-and-the-map"&gt;My Reading of The Keys and The Map&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;pre class="highlight"&gt;&lt;code&gt;ESC     The escape or exit key
123     Important number keys: I, US, ALL
^°      Instructions for number keys, lots of space still
4       Bad luck number, right after important ONES
5%      Sounds like someone else's rule
6&amp;amp;      SIX AND (SIX AND (SIX)), oops, slipped a bit there
7/{     SEVEN, cut, EMBRACE
8([     Infinity, protect and TRUE STRIKE
9)]     Opposite of SIX, detach, IMMOVABLE WALL
0=}     DAMPFLÖCK smiley face with diving googles
ß?\     some German thing? More work I guess
´`      A roof
'Bksp'  Corrects errors when you TYPE TOO FAST
ENTER   NEWLINE, sends the message of GOD
üöä     or other regionals, for fast regional proof
TAB     Close to instructions, for aiming
GODKEY  Speak in the TRUE VOICE OF GOD; but RTFM first
Shift   Temp. god speak, may be mistaken at times
&amp;lt;|&amp;gt;     Looks like some space ship, for computers
CTRL    YOU JUST NEED TO TAKE IT, but easy friends
ALT     Another modifier, when CTRL doesn't work
SUPER   or windows or apple key, more WÖRK
SPACE   Easy to hit, important and big KEY
,;      joining words, thoughts
.:      joining sentences, highlighting NEXT
-_      partially forgotten SAD FACE, for quitters!
HASH    number sign, high command
+~*     stay positive, vibe, SEE THE LIGHT
ins, del, home, pg up etc., just some words
F1-F12  Function keys, for potions, assign at WILL&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Writing Executive Summaries</title>
      <link>https://oliz.io/blog/2022/executive-summaries/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Mar 2022 10:42:50 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://oliz.io/blog/2022/executive-summaries/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;You know what always helped me acting upon the wisdom I read in BOOKs:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Writing summaries, or cheat sheets&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can do so even if you haven't read the entire book, yet!
Then you should just put a version or volume number on it, that you can increment when you gain further noteworthy learnings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="bible-example"&gt;Bible Example&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the last few years I started reading the Bible (New Testament, in German). So, please ignore the German words, I'll provide a translation for the summarized ones below the photo:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Summary and Bible" src="bible-summary.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Translation of the German words in the summary, so far:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="highlight"&gt;&lt;code&gt;learn, read, train
create, write
get rid of, improve
rest, play
invest, sell&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;h2 id="what-if-the-summary-is-wronglacking"&gt;What if the Summary is Wrong/Lacking?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As with books, you then add an additional edition counter.
E.g. the above executive summary lacks basics like the Golden Rule, which seemed to obvious to me, so I omitted it.
A 2nd edition of vol. 1 could include: "Be nice to others". Easy!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>XMRig on Android</title>
      <link>https://oliz.io/blog/2022/xmrig-on-android.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 12 Feb 2022 19:40:33 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://oliz.io/blog/2022/xmrig-on-android.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The Nobel Prize "for Economics" is fake, but money and blockchain are real? If your answer to this is "YES!", you may proceed at your own liability...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Install Termux&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Install &lt;code&gt;proot-distro&lt;/code&gt; package in Termux&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Setup an Ubuntu environment
    &lt;pre class="highlight"&gt;&lt;code class="language-bash"&gt;proot-distro install ubuntu
proot-distro login ubuntu&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Follow &lt;a href="https://xmrig.com/docs/miner/build/ubuntu"&gt;https://xmrig.com/docs/miner/build/ubuntu&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;pre class="highlight"&gt;&lt;code class="language-bash"&gt;apt update &amp;amp;&amp;amp; apt upgrade
apt-get install git build-essential cmake automake libtool autoconf
git clone https://github.com/xmrig/xmrig.git
# Change donation rate if desired
mkdir xmrig/build &amp;amp;&amp;amp; cd xmrig/scripts
./build_deps.sh &amp;amp;&amp;amp; cd ../build
cmake .. -DXMRIG_DEPS=scripts/deps
make -j$(nproc)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Start &lt;code&gt;xmrig&lt;/code&gt; with minimal configuration
    &lt;pre class="highlight"&gt;&lt;code class="language-bash"&gt;modprobe msr # if supported by the system
./xmrig -o ${POOL} -u ${WALLET} -k --tls&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bonus: &lt;a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/Monero/comments/sse4b1/stop_minexmr_p2pool_guide_how_to_mine_xmr_using/"&gt;How to mine on p2pool (nice summary in one of the posts)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Remove snap(d)</title>
      <link>https://oliz.io/blog/2022/remove-snap.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Apr 2022 14:49:25 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://oliz.io/blog/2022/remove-snap.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Sometimes it may be desired to get packages from &lt;code&gt;apt&lt;/code&gt; instead of &lt;code&gt;snap&lt;/code&gt;,
e.g. the Chromium snap doesn't have hardware acceleration for video conferences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="highlight"&gt;&lt;code&gt;# Remove all snap packages
snap list
sudo snap remove --purge $SNAP_NAME

# Remove cache
sudo rm -rf /var/cache/snapd/
sudo apt autoremove --purge snapd gnome-software-plugin-snap
rm -rf ~/snap

# Block snap from auto-installing
sudo apt-mark hold snapd
sudo apt install gnome-software&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On Mastery</title>
      <link>https://oliz.io/blog/2022/on-mastery.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 13 Mar 2022 21:56:15 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://oliz.io/blog/2022/on-mastery.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;No master without students.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is age-old wisdom coming in various iterations and examples.
Here are some.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="in-art-eg-paintings-classical-music"&gt;In art (e.g. paintings, classical music)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some great artists were recognized at their time, amassed great fortune and fame, had plenty of contemporary students to teach to and learn from.
Others also did great work, but died alone, poor, without recognition, without any direct students.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, you can seemingly fail as a master during your lifetime.
But if you were determined and truly great, you will get redeemed by your future students.
Across time.
Ultimately, the joke is on them: because you aren't around anymore to be asked questions and the students were "too late" to get the cues, they now need to try extra hard to understand! Haha!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="in-martial-arts-japanese-shuhari-and-karate"&gt;In martial arts: Japanese &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shuhari"&gt;Shuhari&lt;/a&gt; and Karate&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Shu ("protect", "obey"): student learns, repeats and practises basics, following the master&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ha ("detach", "digress"): the master student, "master" (1st kyu [highest brown belt], 1st dan [first black belt]) is at the high of their ability and execution, knowing all the relevant stuff and realizing they aren't the first to reach this point. Maybe they challenge the master to include or adapt things with a fresh view. The master student may lead the dojo in the master's absence or on their behalf.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ri ("leave", "separate"): master on the path to true mastery perpetuating their great art. By applying, displaying and teaching. By breaking down and questioning learned forms, movements. Together with new students, both master and students lift the art to "go with the times", "stay current" and thus real.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Karate:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Earlier Okinawan people practiced mixed martial arts (similar to Chinese Kung Fu), incorporated their available tools and weapons to repel pirate raiders. This laid the foundation for modern day Judo and Karate-Do ("Karate" literally first meant "Chinese Hand"). Practitioners trained all kinds of techniques to overpower and kill (e.g. sweeps, throws, chokes, grappling). They trained hard, harming their body in the long term, but this was appropriate to handle the raiders. Otherwise, they would have not reached old age anyway.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Karate in the military: Karate was used as physical education. Low, wide stances and punches don't make sense in industrialized, armed conflict, but the strengthening, endurance and discipline aspects go long ways also in war. Masters were aware and adapted teachings to circumstances.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Modern day: Anyone (incl. women, children, &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=SaXU8_soOBQ"&gt;impaired people&lt;/a&gt;) can train this and adapt the forms to their bodily limits and try to reach further. &lt;a href="https://oliz.io/blog/2021/sensomotorik-und-handlungskompetenz/"&gt;Karate can be trained till old age with great health, motor, cognitive benefits&lt;/a&gt;, without ever getting into a real fight. Even if that's just due to anticipation, avoiding fights in the first place instead of physical prowess. The "way of the empty hand" (contemporary reading of "Karate"), so to say.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite, fighting capability and spirit are still very important for further propagation of the art. Masters take this into account and screen for the "warrior heart". Quitters don't win and won't graduate the black belt. Even if they get it while lacking quality, maybe the master's attention slipped and didn't notice the flaw in character. Then they will doubt themselves, see how poor their forms are compared to other black belts, other masters and they will eventually stop wearing the belt, quitting Karate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="in-education-and-academia"&gt;In education and academia&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you achieve a "master title" in academia or your "master diploma" as a craftsman (f/m/d),
you have demonstrated that you are at the top of your game, know all the relevant stuff and are ready to be released onto the world without training wheels.
Some of those masters teach students, take apprentices, become doctors, professors. Others may create such great things, that even without taking direct students, future students will study their work for insights.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="in-mathematics-students-t-distribution"&gt;In mathematics: &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Student%27s_t-distribution"&gt;Student's t-distribution&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So this "math master", instead of getting his name attributed to his works (like most of the masters before and after him), he chose to delay credit (it got attributed anyway, check the linked Wikipedia article) and by choosing a considerate pseudonym spread the idea that even a master must be a perpetual student.
Any proper math teacher or professor will explain the name, that the distribution is really called "student" not because a person was named like this, but because the person wanted to highlight that they saw themselves as "eternal math students" and that there always will be something left to study.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="in-popular-culture-star-wars"&gt;In popular culture: Star Wars&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mastery is explored extensively in Star Wars.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Galen Erso (&lt;a href="https://starwars.fandom.com/wiki/Rogue_One"&gt;Rogue One&lt;/a&gt;) is a master weapon builder, engineer and scientist. He is forced to finish the most powerful weapon ever: the Death Star. Knowing that the evil empire will discard him after, he planned a long-running plot: He built in weak point by design to be found and relayed to the rebels/resistance by his daughter. The rebels then studied it hard and destroyed the Death Star (+ later iterations). Each time with greater ease. They basically achieved "undo evil powerful weapons" mastery, as their master Galen Erso intended with his master work. The incapable evil empire couldn't fix the inherent design flaws, because they weren't masters and also poor students. It took a while, but after the 3rd station got destroyed they got the message and stopped building "just another Death Star"™, but went with a more conservative approach "even bigger fleet". Well, no mastery there either, judging by how it turned out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jedi: A Jedi master may take multiple padawans over the course of his life. A padawan may become a master and teach padawans themselves. Potentially, this ensures greater spread and higher numbers. Some may disagree and may part with the Jedi order to instead become...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sith: Who took mastery to the extreme ("absolutes" so to say, hehe) with the "Rule of Two": At any given time there may be only one Sith Lord with only one Sith Apprentice. To become the lord, the apprentice needs to kill the master. Either by sheer force/power or by great wit/deceit, whatever is more suitable for continuation of the Sith given the circumstances.
The apprentice fails when the lord kills them instead. The master grows more powerful with this, too: Learning how the student tried to outplay, what better qualities to look for in the next apprentice. Darth Sidious had and outgrew multiple apprentices until ultimately killed and both sides of the force merged.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you see, the pattern is pretty omnipresent and told in various forms.
To reach as many humans as possible.
I'm sure, you can find further examples!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="on-students"&gt;On Students&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now we talked a lot about "masters" and "mastery", but little about students.
That's because there isn't much to say, if you understood it to this point:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;No such thing as "bad students".&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That's also common wisdom and it's self-evident from the very word: &lt;em&gt;studere&lt;/em&gt; is Latin for "to sincerely try".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So the only task a student has, is to try. Try to understand the masters and their greatness. Try to outshine them.
They don't necessarily need to succeed. They may fail, that's fine.
They then may look for a different master, a different topic and try again. Others may take their place instead.
The only bad student is a student who doesn't try, in which case they aren't a "student" by the very sense of the word. A student giving up, simply ceases to be a student. Not offending any master, any craft or anything really, but themselves. By wasting their own time. A master claiming in front of poorly performing students that "they are wasting the master's time" isn't reflecting enough on what he could learn from the student's failures. At the same time, the master implicitly asks them to try harder.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus "bad student" is an inherent oxymoron, while "excellent master" is an obvious tautology.
If we don't think like this, e.g. having the need to distinguish between "masters" and "great masters". Then, maybe, we have watered down the term "master" a bit too much.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, I hope this post corrected the image. Highlighting that obtaining mastery is a perpetual, self-correcting process. Sounds a lot like all of life, huh?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="on-mediocrity"&gt;On Mediocrity&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What happens with the masters who aren't good enough and the students who never achieved mastery in anything ever?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mediocrity will simply be forgotten.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In other words, the opening sentence of this post could be reworded to:
&lt;em&gt;If your art, craft etc. dies with you, you were a lesser than all the masters before you!&lt;/em&gt;
Even if your trade is still relevant to humankind, new students will simply skip past you to the masters before you! The joke is on you there! Ouch!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="in-architecture-pyramids-and-saint-basils-cathedral"&gt;In architecture: Pyramids and &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Saint_Basil%27s_Cathedral"&gt;Saint Basil's Cathedral&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The master builders of the pyramids got buried with their pharaohs.
Did we forgot how to build pyramids? Yes!
Do we know how the pyramids were built? Not quite, but we have some ideas!
Do we really need to build further pyramids? Probably not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Did we learn something anyway? Yeah, for instance:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Stone and paintings last long time, even longer than the language that is used to write the hieroglyphs!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Air-tight interlocking sandstone is awesome and very rigid!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Air-tight locked rooms and darkness breed deadly fungus and when opened you get very sick and die&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Since the construction is so timeless, maybe important information wasn't encoded in language, but in architecture?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Did the pharaohs have a bad intention bury their builders with them?
We don't know! Maybe it doesn't matter, either!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h2 id="personal-anecdotes"&gt;Personal Anecdotes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Form my software engineering life:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I.
I once interviewed an applicant for a (senior) software development position.
Previously, the candidate worked in a consulting firm literally called "senior dev only" specializing in renting out senior developers to needy companies. I wondered, how that'd work and how they'd know that they are all "senior developers". Was it by age (to fight blatant agism, let's mean "years of experience")? Was by the amount of money they charge gullible companies?
The candidate wasn't that good by my judgement, some knowledge at display was outdated. We ended up not hiring the candidate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;II.
Similarly, some very capable (by my judgement), senior colleagues left for another company.
That company had huge financial backing and was hiring "senior devs only" to finish an ambitious project on a tight one year schedule.
I didn't check back again, but here are my assumptions of possible outcomes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Too many cooks spoil the broth: Each senior dev has their own ideas how things should work, lots of meetings, agreement takes ages. Eventually, the thing is too late and over budget, oops!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Most likely, the senior devs realize the situation, evaluate available abilities, preferences and requirements. Naturally, some of them lead and push bigger design decisions. Others step down a bit and follow. In this case, the company could have hired less seniors and more juniors and probably achieved a similar result, cheaper. Oops! Don't tell that the bean counters!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In magical fairytale land, all the seniors devs got along in perfect harmony. They delivered a high quality solution, under budget, on time. After this great achievement, all the great achievers head out to the next challenge (other project, other company). The software works, eventually requirements change, nobody's there anymore to understand the thing and there's limited documentation/onboarding/handover material. What's there can only be understood by great achievers. Eventually, the company hires further great achievers which attest a re-write is needed at great cost. Oops!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;III.
So I was teaching "modern" software engineering for one semester (2020-2021 during pandemic) at university, which is a separate blog post still in the making©.
The gist is, I worked my way backwards from primary motive of "working software" (duh, surprise!) in the Agile Manifesto.
Close to the end of semester, I got evaluated by the students.
Besides all the benevolent feedback which I received, the most helpful one was (paraphrased):
"Agile is pseudo-scientific mumbojumbo and I wished the lecturer would have instead focussed more on &lt;em&gt;real engineering&lt;/em&gt;, not personal anecdotes."
Ufff, that hit hard! Quite a revelation!
Even if I may have failed that student, it pushed me to try harder.
I openly motivated my strategy again, so hopefully the rest of them got the message.
Overall, the students tried hard despite the suboptimal Corona situation, did very well in required presentations and the exam.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rousseau in Two Sentences</title>
      <link>https://oliz.io/blog/2022/rousseau.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Apr 2022 07:51:34 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://oliz.io/blog/2022/rousseau.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Humans are as free, healthy and happy as it is possible in nature, when they focus on work a single person can handle.
Unhappiness and inequality stem from society and its need to forage, own, depend, compare and compete, which promotes innate human differences (e.g. in ability, preferences, talents).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>P. Levels: Startup Cycle and More</title>
      <link>https://oliz.io/blog/2022/plevels-startup-cycle.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Apr 2022 19:41:43 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://oliz.io/blog/2022/plevels-startup-cycle.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://levels.io/"&gt;P. Levels&lt;/a&gt; pretty famous indie maker and &lt;a href="https://nomadlist.com/"&gt;digital nomad&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His startup cycle:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Idea&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Build it!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Launch it!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Grow it!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Monetize!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Automate!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Exit!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His predictions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Marriage is disappearing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Relationship churn is fast&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Home ownership is disappearing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;People will travel more&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Different family units&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The collective existential crisis due to automation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We have remote now, we want async&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What hit home most for me:
He adviced on building solutions to one's own problems. Then grow organically, e.g. by using the above formula.
&lt;strong&gt;If others built solutions to all your problems already, you are likely boring and your life just isn't very original!&lt;/strong&gt;
Uff!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>J. Romero: Programming Principles</title>
      <link>https://oliz.io/blog/2022/j-romero.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Apr 2022 06:18:33 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://oliz.io/blog/2022/j-romero.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;From &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Romero"&gt;John Romero&lt;/a&gt;'s standard talk on the early days of "id Software", which I also witnessed in person once:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No prototypes. &lt;strong&gt;Just make the game&lt;/strong&gt;, polish as you go. Don't depend on polish happening later. Always maintain constantly shippable code.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It is incredibly important that your &lt;strong&gt;game can always be run by your team&lt;/strong&gt;. Bulletproof your engine by providing defaults upon load failure.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Keep your code absolutely simple&lt;/strong&gt;. Keep looking at your functions and figure out how you can simplify further.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Great tools&lt;/strong&gt; help make great games. Spend as much time on tools as possible.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We are our own best testing team and should &lt;strong&gt;never allow anyone else to experience bugs or see the game crash&lt;/strong&gt;. Don't waste others' time. Test thoroughly before checking in your code.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;As soon as you see a bug, you fix it!&lt;/strong&gt; Do not continue on. If you don't fix your bugs your new code will be built on a buggy codebase and ensure an unstable foundation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use a superior system than your target.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Write your code for this game only – not for a future game. &lt;strong&gt;You're going to be writing new code later because you'll be smarter&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Encapsulate functionality&lt;/strong&gt; to ensure design consistency. This minimizes mistakes and saves design time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Try to &lt;strong&gt;code transparently&lt;/strong&gt;. Tell your lead and peers exactly how you are going to solve your current task and &lt;strong&gt;get feedback and advice&lt;/strong&gt;. Do not treat game programming like each coder is a black box. The project could go off the rails and cause delays.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Programming is a creative art form based in logic&lt;/strong&gt;. Every programmer is different and will code differently. It's the output that matters.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sources:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=QKXj_OW96YQ"&gt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=QKXj_OW96YQ&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.heise.de/newsticker/meldung/John-Romero-Von-id-Softwares-Anfaengen-und-World-of-Warcraft-Sucht-3296840.html"&gt;https://www.heise.de/newsticker/meldung/John-Romero-Von-id-Softwares-Anfaengen-und-World-of-Warcraft-Sucht-3296840.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>F. Lebowitz on self-help books</title>
      <link>https://oliz.io/blog/2022/fran-lebowitz.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Apr 2022 16:05:54 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://oliz.io/blog/2022/fran-lebowitz.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;"Is it a self-help book?" - "It is, it is helping myself"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=G46BVjjkDfA&amp;amp;t=1774s"&gt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=G46BVjjkDfA&amp;amp;t=1774s&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Jack Ma Life Advice</title>
      <link>https://oliz.io/blog/2022/jack-ma.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 16 Apr 2022 08:46:52 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://oliz.io/blog/2022/jack-ma.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I didn't record the source of the following in my notes, but it was probably some Youtube video or article on &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jack_Ma"&gt;Jack Ma&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Till 25: learn, do mistakes, be a good student&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Till 30: Follow someone, learn from them&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Till 40: Work for yourself&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Till 50: Do the things you are good at&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Till 60: Work for the young people&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Over 60: Spend time for yourself&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="on-business"&gt;On Business&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Focus on company culture! Focus on, in order:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Customers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Employees (often overlooked)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Investors&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Have a good (personal, company) name! Reputation is key!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Follow Larry Page's "Toothbrush Rule": People should want to use a product/service worth billions at least twice a day!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
